<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the peaceable and friendly address to the non-conformists against the ansvver lately given to it. In which the obligation to conform to the constitutions of the established church is maintained and vindicated. The answerers objections solv'd; and his calumnies refuted.</title>
            <author>Synge, Edward, 1659-1741.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 174 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S6377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221946</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99833190</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99833190</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37665</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37665)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2065:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the peaceable and friendly address to the non-conformists against the ansvver lately given to it. In which the obligation to conform to the constitutions of the established church is maintained and vindicated. The answerers objections solv'd; and his calumnies refuted.</title>
                  <author>Synge, Edward, 1659-1741.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J. B. and S.P. at the back of Dick's Coffee-House, in Skinner-Row, for John Foster, bookseller,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Edward Synge.</note>
                  <note>Gathered in 2's.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37665:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37665:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE Peaceable and Friendly ADDRESS TO THE <hi>Non-Conformiſts:</hi> AGAINST THE ANSVVER Lately given to it.</p>
            <p>In which the Obligation to Conform to the Conſtitutions of the Eſtabliſhed Church is Maintained and Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The Anſwerers Objections Solv'd; And his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies Refuted.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Thou ſhalt not bear falſe Witneſs againſt thy Neighbour,</hi> 
               <bibl>Exod. 20. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>DUBLIN: Printed by <hi>J. B.</hi> and <hi>S. P.</hi> at the back of <hi>Dick</hi>'s Coffee-Houſe in <hi>Skinner-Row,</hi> for <hi>John Foſter,</hi> Bookſeller, 1698.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37665:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37665:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:37665:3"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>IN Epiſt. Ded. near the latter end, for <hi>diſiagenious</hi> read <hi>diſingenuous.</hi> p. 14. l. 12. for <hi>prepoſition</hi> read <hi>propoſition,</hi> l. 30. for <hi>Auther tell</hi> read <hi>Author tells.</hi> p. 15. l. 16. for <hi>profeſſions</hi> read <hi>profeſſion.</hi> p. 22. l. 24. for <hi>forbidded</hi> read <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden.</hi> p. 24. l. 26. for <hi>other</hi> read <hi>others,</hi> l. 40. for <hi>theſe</hi> read <hi>thoſe.</hi> p. 31. l. 31. no comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> after <hi>preſſes.</hi> p. 48. l. 1. for <hi>payly</hi> read <hi>dayly.</hi> p. 50. l. 1. for <hi>places</hi> read <hi>place.</hi> p. 56. l. 23. for <hi>ungratefull read ungratefully,</hi> l. 38. for <hi>bulldle</hi> read <hi>bundle.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:37665:3"/>
            <head>To His Grace Michael, Lord Arch-Biſhop of Ardmagh, Primate and Metropolitan of all Ireland.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen I writ my <hi>Peaceable and Friendly Addreſs to the Nonconformiſts,</hi> it was my deſign to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs my ſelf ſo clearly as to give no juſt occaſion for miſtake or cavill; and ſo calmly as to give no Offence to any Man, except he would be angry with me, either for being of a diſſerent o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion from him, or elſe for fairly offering my Reaſons why I am ſo.</p>
            <p>I was therefore in hopes, that if any of our Nonconforming Brethren ſhould think fit to anſwer what I had written, he would lay aſide all heat and animoſity, and all ſuch Exceptions as are manifestly trifling and impertinent; and only urge what might be of ſome real strength and moment in the Controverſy; and that with the ſame Mildneſs and Charity as I had endeavoured to do before him.</p>
            <p>But inſtead hereof an Adverſary has lately appeared againſt me, who, as he ſeems to have but very little regard either to Charity, or even to Truth; ſo has he taken very much pains to perplex and tangle, inſtead of clearing and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>plaining the diſpute that is between us. And as he has raked together what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever dirt he could to throw at the Church, the Law, and Your
<pb facs="tcp:37665:4"/> Grace, as well as at me (but still without any juſt ground for all his Calumnies) ſo has he, by the ambiguity of his Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy of his way of Reaſoning, and his Miſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is of the Holy Scripture, Raiſed ſuch a miſt of Sophiſtry in thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Controverſy, as may p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rhaps dazle the eyes of an un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ry Rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, or impoſe upon ſome of his own Party, whoſe pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>judic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> will n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t permit th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m impartially to conſider things, but c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nnot, as I c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ceive, have any manner of Influence upon any ſober and underſtanding Man; Except it may be to move him to have the worſe opinion of that Cauſe, which is maintained and uph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld after this manner, and of that Perſon, whoever he be, that thus violates the plain Laws of God, while he pretends his Conſcience to be ſo tender as that he cannot Conform to the Conſtitutions of the Eſtabliſhed Church.</p>
            <p>To this diſingenious Man I have here returned an Anſwer; And have done it with as much mildneſs as I thought the Caſe would hear: Yet not forbearing ſometimes to expreſs a juſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation against ſuch palpable prevarications as I have Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed him of. And whatever my performance is I humbly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to your Graces cenſure: And with my moſt hearty Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for your Graces both Temporal and Eternal Happyneſs, I remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Cork, <date>October 1. 1698.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Graces Moſt Obedient Chaplain and Moſt Obliged Humble Servant Edward Synge.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:37665:4"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE OF THE Peaceable and Friendly ADDRESS TO THE <hi>NON-Conformiſts:</hi> AGAINST THE ANSVVER Lately given to it.</head>
            <p>THE whole Book, againſt a part of which I am to make my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, conſiſts of three parts: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>irſt, A Preface <hi>to the Proteſtant Reader.</hi> Secondly, <hi>Animadve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſions on the Defence of the Anſwer, &amp;c.</hi> And thirdly <hi>An Anſwer to</hi> my <hi>Peaceable and Friendly Addreſs to the Nonconformiſts.</hi> With the Second of theſe I am not concerned; And therefore ſhall ſet my ſelf to conſider only the firſt and third.</p>
            <p>In the firſt Paragraph of the <hi>Preface</hi> I am repreſented as one of thoſe who <hi>judge it their Intereſt to miſrepreſent to the World them they are pleaſed to call Nonconforming Brethren, as a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>ous and S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hiſmatical People;</hi> And as a Man who am inclined to be <hi>wiſe in</hi> my <hi>own conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> (a caſe more deſperate than that of a fool)</hi> which therefore the Author out of <hi>Compaſſion</hi> to me, and ſuch as I am, <hi>endeavours</hi> in this his Book to <hi>prevent.</hi> But ſince he does not offer any inſtance of what I have ſaid or done to juſtify this odious Character
<pb facs="tcp:37665:5"/> which he ventures to inſinuate of me; I think it is enough for me to ſay that they who know me better than he can poſſibly do (amongſt whom I believe I may reckon ſome of my Nonconforming Neighbours) have I hope a different opinion of me. And I entreat him to conſider that as he ought not to ſuggeſt ſuch things to the prejudice of another without very good proof (for <hi>aſſirmanti incumbit probatio,</hi> as he obſerves <hi>pag.</hi> 98.) ſo has our bleſſed Saviour pronounced a very ſevere Sentence againſt thoſe who are ſo ready to give ſuch ſort o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Language to their <hi>Brother, Mat.</hi> 5 22. Which title I hope I ſhall never juſtly forfeit, notwithſtanding that he is pleaſed to let me know that he is not <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ond of that Relation</hi> to me, <hi>pag.</hi> 96.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſuggeſted a very i'l Character of me, which I hope I do not deſerve; In the next place he gives a very good one of the Nonconformiſts, which I never denied but they may, and I hope they do, very well deſerve. But however I think he ſhould have taken a little better care to prevent ſome uncharitable miſapprehenſions which may be apt to ariſe in Mens minds, through the uncautiouſneſs of ſome of thoſe Expreſſions which he here makes uſe of. As, for Example, when he tells us that the Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts <hi>are not the idle and conſuming Caterpillars of the Nation;</hi> Does not this ſeem to look as if he would inſinuate, either that we were ſuch our Selves, or elſe had ſo accounted and miſrepreſented them? For if no one had ever thought either them or us to be <hi>idle and conſuming Caterpillers,</hi> to what end and purpoſe ſhould he ſo particularly inform the World that they are not ſuch? And again (to omit other inſtances) when he tells us that <hi>their fear towards God is not taught by the Commandments of Men;</hi> would not ſome Men be apt to collect from hence that, in his Judgment at leaſt, our fear towards God is taught by the Commandments of Men? For when Men do thus give Negative Characters of themſelves, it is uſually conſtrued as if they intended them for poſitive ones of thoſe from whom they ſeem thus to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh themſelves. I am unwilling to believe that he purpoſely deſigned theſe and ſome other no leſs groundleſs than odious Inſinuations againſt thoſe of the Eſtabliſhed Church, which ſeem to lye couched in this Paragraph: But when we conſider how prevalent paſſion and ill nature are in ſome Men of all Perſuaſions; I think we cannot be too carefull to avoid ſuch Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions as may any way ſerve to adminiſter falſe pretences to them.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing this account which he has given of the Nonconformiſts to be no more than what in juſtice belongs to every ſincere and well meaning Man among them; Yet may not even ſuch Men as theſe be miſtaken in ſome things? And ſince I have only endeavoured fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly to lay their miſtakes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them (without deſigning in any other thing, in the leaſt, to detract from them) and that in ſuch ſoft and gentle Language, that even this Author allows that there is <hi>a ſtudied Temper and Calmneſs in my words, pag.</hi> 96. I will
<pb facs="tcp:37665:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> appeal to the Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cience of every ſober and peaceable Chriſtian whether what I have done does any way deſerve ſuch ſevere and bitter Reſentments as this Anſwer carries in it againſt me.</p>
            <p>In the third and laſt Paragraph of his Preface he briefly ſets forth the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty,</hi> as he ſuppoſes, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> what the Nonconformiſts deſire. In the former part whereof I for my part do, and always did, fully agree with him. I would indeed, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it lay in my power, perſuade them all to Comform them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Worſhip and Diſcipline of the Eſtabliſhed Church; becauſe I am of opinion that they are bound in Conſcience ſo to do; for which I have briefly ſuggeſted my reaſons in my late <hi>Addreſs</hi> to them. But ſince all that has been ſaid and written in this Controverſy does not convince them, I think it is very ſit that they ſhould be left to <hi>ſland or fall to their own Maſter:</hi> And that a full and free <hi>Liberty</hi> ſhould be granted them <hi>to ſerve God accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to</hi> thoſe <hi>Principles</hi> which he mentions, with a <hi>relie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> from</hi> all <hi>Penal Laws</hi> whatſoever; As long as they are ready to give the Civil Government the ſame aſſurance that other Subjects do of their Loyal and Peaceable demean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or: And this Author does me very much wrong in endeavouring to make the World believe that I have ſaid or ſuggeſted any thing to the contrary; as we ſhall more fully ſee hereafter. But as to the other Clauſe of their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition; <hi>viz. That no new ones be forged to their prejudice;</hi> He has left the meaning of it ſo doubtful, having ſet it down only in thoſe general terms; that it is not to be anſwered, until the ſenſe of it be firſt determined. It then his meaning be <hi>that no new</hi> penal Laws be forged againſt the Non-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts; they need not at this time make that their requeſt; becauſe they know very well that the contrary is not ſo much as thought of, or in the leaſt propoſed by any one. But if it be <hi>that no new</hi> Laws whatſoever <hi>be forged</hi> or contrived any way <hi>to their prejudice</hi> (which ſeems to be the literal purport of his words) no, not to cut them ſhort in any thing, but that they ſhould to all intents and purpoſes enjoy all manner of Priviledges, and be equally quallified with thoſe of the Legal Church for all places and employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whatſoever <hi>(Epiſcopal Grandeur, Juriſdiction and Revenue for their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,</hi> being all that he has excepted). If this I ſay, be the thing they would have; they may perhaps think their demands to be but <hi>juſt,</hi> becauſe they apprehend themſelves to be in the right: But it ſeems ſtrange that they ſhould give this out for ſo <hi>modeſt a Petition</hi> as this Author would inſinuate; as if herein they asked <hi>leſs</hi> than what in reaſon they might; And if this be their <hi>modeſt Petition,</hi> what more with they or their ſucceſſors in the next Generation proceed to demand, if ever they ſhould venture to aſſume a little <hi>Confidence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having thus done with the Preface, I paſs by the ſecond part of his Book, as I ſaid, and addreſs my ſelf to the third. And here the <hi>Doctor</hi> (as in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb facs="tcp:37665:6"/> he is pleaſed to call me, for I never took the degree or paſſed by that Title) in the entrance is taxed of downright <hi>Diſingenuity,</hi> as having, under the Title of a <hi>Peaceable and Friendly Addreſs to the Non-Conformiſts,</hi> publiſhed <hi>a Libel againſt them;</hi> and under <hi>a ſtudied Temper and calmneſs of Words, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign'd a windy Storm and Tempeſt; with good Words and fair Speeches lying in wait to deceive; Having war in his heart</hi> while <hi>his words are ſmoother than but<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> which tho' they <hi>were ſofter than Oyl,</hi> yet are <hi>as drawn Swords, while by them he is ſtirring up thoſe who bear not the Sword in vain to imploy it againſt his Nonconforming Brethren, as he calls them,</hi> pag. 95. 96. But ſince he does not ſo much as <hi>offer</hi> the leaſt <hi>ſhew</hi> of proof to make good this heavy Charge; I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think that any ſober man will have the worſe opinion of me for all this that he has alledged againſt me. God, who is the only ſearcher of hearts, knows that <hi>in my heart there is no war</hi> againſt the Non-conformiſts; Except I muſt <hi>therefore become their Enemy becauſe I tell them the Truth:</hi> Nor have I the leaſt deſign <hi>to deceive</hi> them; But on the contrary, to make them truly ſenſible of what I am perſwaded is their Duty. There is not one railing or ſcurrilous Expreſſion in all my <hi>Addreſs</hi> to them; and therefore why it ſhould be called a <hi>Libel,</hi> I cannot ſee: As for the <hi>Stormy wind and Tempeſt</hi> he talks of, I know not where it is, except in his own imagination; and if my words be as <hi>drawn Swords,</hi> it can be nothing but the Evidence of Truth, which touches his Conſcience, that makes them ſeem ſo to him; for I am ſure there is no manner of <hi>ſharpneſs</hi> in the Style or Language. But whereas he accuſes me of <hi>ſtirring up</hi> the Magiſtracy <hi>to employ the Sword againſt them;</hi> I deſire him to produce but one ſingle paſſage or expreſſion in my Addreſs, which does but <hi>look that way,</hi> and I promiſe him that I will publickly retract it: But if he cannot do this (as it is moſt evident he cannot) I leave it to his conſcience whether he ought not to beg Gods pardon for inventing ſo ſoul a ſlander againſt me, for which, I bleſs God, I never gave the leaſt oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: For to perſecute or puniſh men that are peaceable and obedient to the Civil Government, on account of their miſtakes in matters of Religion or the Worſhip of God, is what I have never failed to declare againſt when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever there was any occaſion for it. And God is my witneſs, that I had not the leaſt thought or deſign tending that way when I writ or publiſhed my addreſs to the Nonconformiſts: Nor can I imagine how any man who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partially conſiders what I have therein offered, can from thence pretend to lay the contrary to my charge.</p>
            <p>Having formerly had the honour of being a Servant to my Lord Primate, I thought it might not be improper, when I put forth that ſmall piece, to make a publick acknowledgment of that honour and reſpect which I bear to his Grace, in a ſhort Epiſtle which I prefixed to it; Wherein amongſt other things, I judged it ſit to take notice what <hi>an Eminent example of Temper and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37665:6"/> Moderation</hi> his Grace has always been, as to all men in general, ſo <hi>to the Diſſenters</hi> in particular: Of which I mention <hi>his mildneſs and lenity, even in thoſe times when it was moſt in his Power to uſe ſeverity towards them,</hi> as a very evident <hi>Demonſtration.</hi> Now altho' one chief deſign of this Paſſage was to recommend a mild and gentle Temper towards the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> as a thing to be approved of, and imitated by all the World; yet this Author cannot let this paſs without his Animadverſion; And therefore he denies the matter of Fact, and gives this as a reaſon for it, namely, becauſe the Non-conformiſts in the North never met with greater ſeverity, than <hi>when the Primate of all</hi> Ireland <hi>and Chancellor rode both upon one Horſe,</hi> as in a court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly manner he is pleaſed to phraſe it. <hi>pag.</hi> 96. Now, beſides that, I have no great reaſon to believe any thing upon the teſtimony of that man, who can lay ſuch ill things to my charge, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> which I know my ſelf to be altogether innocent, as I have but juſt now remarked; ſuppoſe that what he ſays were true, yet ſtill his inference plainly appears to have no more Logick than good nature in it: For if the Diſſenters were more hardly uſed, whilſt his Grace held both thoſe honourable Stations of Lord Primate and Lord Chancellor, than they had been at other times (which yet I never heard before) yet will it not follow, but that he might bear a very mild and gentle temper towards them: For it is very poſſible that ſevere methods may be uſed by a Government, and yet neither the Lord Primate, nor the Lord Chancellor, be the Promoter of them; But rather, it may be, mitigate that rigour of Law, which others perhaps might be inclined to the utmoſt to put in execution.</p>
            <p>But he ſeems in a manner deſirous <hi>pag.</hi> 97. to be <hi>put upon the proof</hi> of what he has ſo odiouſly ſuggeſted againſt my Lord Primate. Now how well ſuch a ſpightful Task may agree with his diſpoſition, I know not: But if there were any neceſſity for ſaying ſuch ill things as he has done, both of his Grace, and of me; more then raiſing the paſſion, and embittering the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of his Party; I think he ought to have proved them, and that beyond exception, at the ſame time when he publiſhed them to the World. For if he would not have theſe things to be believed, why does he aſſert them? But if he would, what reaſon is there why he ſhould not prove them? It cannot be any tenderneſs to his Grace's reputation, or mine; For he has en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured, as much as he can, to wound them by accuſing us; and what elſe it ſhould be, except the want of clear and ſufficient Evidence, I cannot imagine,</p>
            <p>I have heard and read of grievous complaints, which both the Epiſcopal and Non-conforming Parties have made of having been hardly dealt with, either by other, as they have had the Power in their hands. Now altho' the former in this Kingdom have ever had this to plead in their Juſtification,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37665:7"/> that they have been warranted by the Law in what they did, which the latter cannot pretend to; yet what good there can be in ripping up paſt Stories of this nature, I know not. Methinks the buſineſs of every good Chriſtian ſhould rather be to heal, than unnec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rily to rub and fret ſuch old ſores; that peace and charity, at the leaſt, may be eſtabliſhed between us, if we cannot all come to be of one oppinion and judgment in all things. But this Author may do as his charity and diſcretion ſhall prompt him: My Lord Primate is not afraid of him; only let him ſay no more againſt him, than what he clearly proves to be true.</p>
            <p>As a good effect of my Lord Primat's moderate and gentle behaviour while he was Biſhop of <hi>Cork,</hi> I took notice that <hi>ſeveral Nonconforming Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters were won by him to receive Ordination at his Hands, and Conform to the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Diſcipline of our Church.</hi> Agai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t which our Author ſuggeſts ſuch things as have neither Truth nor Charity in them. For he takes it for granted that thoſe Miniſters <hi>renounced their former Ordination,</hi> which was by <hi>Presbyters;</hi> and therefore cenſures this whole matter as the <hi>effect not of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration; but rather in his Grace o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Prelatick Domination, and an uncharitable condemning of the Foreign Reformed Churches,</hi> who <hi>want Epiſcopal Ordination:</hi> And, in the Miniſters that were ſo Ordained, of the <hi>love of the World more than any other Arguments</hi> that were uſed to convince them, <hi>pag.</hi> 97. But ſure if this uncharitable Man did not take ſome extraordinary delight to put al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways the <hi>worſt</hi> Conſtruction upon things, where any of the Eſtabliſhed Church are concerned, he would never take upon him at this rate to judge the Hearts and Conſciences of other M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, which can only be known to Almighty God; And he would have contented himſelf in ſaying that how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever my Lord Primate and thoſe Miniſters who were ſo Ordained might poſſibly act according to the genuine dictates of their own Perſuaſion; Yet that they were guilty of a great Error in what they did; which would have been as much as was neceſſary to be oſſered on his part; without an <hi>uncha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable condemning</hi> of his Brethren, who ought not, without evident reaſon, to be thus judged of inſincerity; being to <hi>ſtand or fall to their own Maſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what if (after all) this matter of Fact, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>theſe Miniſters Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced their former Ordination,</hi> which he ſo conſidently ſuppoſes; be a meer Fable and Invention, without any other ground but ſome Mens Uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Imagination? I have heard indeed this Matter, of Renouncing their former Ordination, ſometimes urged in the behalf of Presbyterian Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, as ſufficient alone to juſtify their Refuſal to be again Ordained by a Biſhop: But upon the beſt enquiry that I could make I could never find that this was any more than a falſe Story Invented by ſome unpeaceable Men, in order to make a breach between the Foreign Reformed Churches and ours. For as ſuch a <hi>Renu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>iation</hi> is not the leaſt required by any Law or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37665:7"/> of our Church, that I know of; ſo could I never yet have any credible Information that any one of our Biſhops ever inſiſted upon any ſuch thing: And the Reader may aſſure himſelf that upon this occaſion, which is now under conſideration, nothing of that nature was required or thought of.</p>
            <p>But here perhaps I ſhall be told that our Author's meaning was no more than this, that they who ſubmitted a ſecond time to be ordained to that Office which they before had Exerciſed, did thereby, at leaſt <hi>implicitly</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce, and acknowledg the nullity of their former ordination. If this were all he intended, methinks he ſhould plainly have ſaid ſo, without ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to inſinuate a matter of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ct which is altogether falſe; However, this pretence it ſelf is eaſily anſwered. If a Man who has a good Title to an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, to obviate ſome ſcruples, or prevent ſome differences which might perhaps ariſe, ſhoul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccept of a new conveyance of what before was in his poſſeſſion; does it fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ow from hence that ſuch a man thereby renounces and diſowns his former right, and acknowledges himſelf to have unjuſtly detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what really was not his own If a Woman who has been lawfully mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, ſhould for the Satisfaction of her Friends, who might have ſome doubts leſt all things might not have been performed as the Law required; conſent to be married again to the ſame Husband, would this be a charitable infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence to conclude, that therefore ſhe <hi>acknowledged</hi> the nullity of her former m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>riag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and conſequently owned her ſelf to be a Whore? Or if a man has for ſome time h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſufficient Commiſſion for any employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and afterwards, for the preventing of ſome occaſional controverſy, which he for ſees may be raiſed, ſhould accept of a new one for the ſame thing, with a proteſlation that he did not thereby renounce or diſown that which he formerly had; and this proteſtation allowed of, would any honeſt or even modeſt Man p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etend that this Man had yet renounced his former Commiſſion; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> thereby owned all that he had done, thereby to be null and void? But that this was &amp; is in effect the caſe of thoſe who, having been formerly ordained by Presbyters, did or do ſubmit themſelves again to be E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopally ordained as our Law requires, I think does moſt evidently appear from the Senſe which my Lord Primate <hi>Bramhall</hi> had of the thing, and his proceeding therein (with whom I preſume it will eaſily be allowed that the preſent Lord Primate, and all the reſt of our Biſhops did, and do ſtill concurr) For, as we are told in his Life, when he required thoſe, in his Dioceſs, who before had been ordained by Presbyters, to receive Epiſcopal Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; they pleaded for themſelves that they were already <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> and therefore needed not again to be <hi>Ordained</hi> ſuch; which was the ſame thing as a <hi>Proteſtation</hi> againſt <hi>Renouncing their former Ordination.</hi> Now this their <hi>Plea</hi> or <hi>Proteſtation</hi> His Grace was ſo far from diſallowing, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring them who had made it to retract it; that on the contrary he ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:37665:8"/> expreſſed his approbation of it on their part; In that he cauſed it to be inſerted in the Letters of Orders of one Worthy and Reverend Gentleman (And therefore I ſuppoſe of all the reſt who were in the like Circumſtances) that <hi>he did not</hi> take upon him <hi>to annihilate his former Ordination, nor to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the validity or invalidity of it; much leſs to condemn all the Ordinations of the foreign Reſormed Churches, whom he leaves to their proper Judge. But</hi> (obſerve) <hi>only to ſupply what was formerly wanting, which the Canons of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Church required; and to provide for the Churches peace, that Schiſm might be avoided, and ſatisfaction given to the Conſciences of the faithful; that they might not any way have a doubt of his Ordination, or reject his Paſtoral performances as if they were invalid.</hi> And I very well remember that one of thoſe Miniſters who were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained by the preſent Lord Primate, gave me once an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what he had done much to the ſame purpoſe, and in words to this effect, <hi>viz.</hi> That when he firſt received Ordination from the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery (in the time of the Troubles) he did it becauſe it was the beſt Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that then he could get to empower him to ſerve God and the Church in the Office of the Miniſtry. But when the Eccleſiaſtical as well as Civil Laws were reſtored to their Force throughout the Kingdom, and Biſhops Eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in every Dioceſs for the Government of the Church; he ſubmitted to be again Epiſcopally Ordained, not that he renounced his former Ordination, or thought he had any reaſon to repent that, as the times then were, he accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of it: But becauſe he looked upon it to be his Duty (now he had it in his power) to become conformable to the Laws and Canons, not of this Church only, but, as he apprehended, of the whole Ancient univerſal Church throughout the World. And now upon a due Conſideration of this whole matter I will appeal to the Conſcience even of any ſober and Charitable Nonconformiſt, whether either my Lord Primate, or thoſe Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters who are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordained by him, do deſerve ſo ſevere and bitter a Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as our Author has ventured to paſs upon them, upon the account of this Tranſaction.</p>
            <p>Having thus animadverted upon my Title page and Epiſtle Dedicatory, he proceeds to <hi>apply himſelf to the Addreſs it ſelf.</hi> In which the firſt thing that I laid down, as the main Foundation of what I had to offer, was, that <hi>it is the Duty of every Chriſtian to promote the Peace and Unity of the Church.</hi> In anſwer to which, becauſe it was impoſſible, to make any exception to the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple it ſelf; he tells me <hi>pag.</hi> 97. That tho' <hi>it hath ever been the honour of peace to be well ſpoken of by all men,</hi> yet is it <hi>the unhappineſs of many men to be under the Dominion of ſuch Luſts as diſenable them to purſue it.</hi> Now if it was his deſign to include me amongſt thoſe <hi>many men</hi> he ſpeaks of (as ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y man I think will be apt to conſtrue this inſinuation) I think, in common <hi>Justice,</hi> he ought to have brought ſome ſolid proof to have made it good: But if it
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37665:8"/> was not his intent to reckon me in this number, methinks, in <hi>Charity,</hi> he ought to have ſaid ſo, and not to have given ſuch an occaſion to the world of faſtening an unjuſt aſperſion upon me. But however he might imagine hereby to bring my <hi>Perſon</hi> under an odium; yet what this has to do with the merit of the <hi>Cauſe</hi> which is in Diſpute, I know not; and therefore have no farther to ſay to it.</p>
            <p>In the next place, in my Addreſs I take it for granted, as a thing which is <hi>too apparent; that there is a ſeparation between the Non-Conformiſts and us; and thereby a Schiſm made in our National Church.</hi> For the latter of which aſſertions our Author taxes me with <hi>Confidence,</hi> and tells me that <hi>the Conſequence is not good,</hi> when I would infer it from the former; Becauſe, ſays he, there <hi>may be a ſeparation without Schiſm (as there is between all the Parochial Churches, which are locally ſeparate)</hi> And <hi>Schiſms where there is no ſeparation of Churches,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 1. pag. 98. But inſtead of juſtifying this conſequence, which he thus finds fault with, I ſhall only tell him that I never deſigned in thoſe words to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance any <hi>Conſequence</hi> at all. That <hi>all Separation</hi> does not neceſſarily imply Schiſm, I readily grant: but yet that <hi>ſome Separations</hi> are certainly Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical, in one or other of the ſeparating Parties, is what I preſume no man in his Wits will deny. Now that there is <hi>ſuch a Separation</hi> between the Non-Conformiſts and the Eſtabliſh't Church as does imply a Schiſm, was, moſt apparently, all that there I intended to ſay; Nor did I think it ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary by any deduction of Conſequences to prove that which I thought ſo evident as not to be denied or doubted of.</p>
            <p>But our Author, it ſeems, will not allow that there is <hi>a Schiſin between them and us;</hi> becauſe <hi>the Presbyterians in the North never joyned with the Eſtabliſhed Church in thoſe things in which we now differ; to wit, Church Government, Liturgy and Ceremonies; and all Diviſion pre-ſuppoſeth a prior Union.</hi> To which I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that wherever there is an <hi>Obligation</hi> to the maintaining of Union and Communion; if that Union and Communion be not accordingly maintained, but denied and renounced; from thence reſults what I mean by a <hi>Schiſm.</hi> Which word I underſtand to ſignifie not only <hi>the Action of Dividing</hi> or ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating what once was joyned and united; but alſo <hi>the State of Separation</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſuch Parties as ſtand obliged to Religious Union, altho' they never were actually united. Now that all Chriſtians are by the Law of God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged, as far as lawfully they can, to maintain Union and Communion one with another, is what I never yet heard denied by any one: And ſince this Union and Communion is not maintained between the Non-Conformiſts and us, it will follow that <hi>there is a Schiſm between us;</hi> and that either we are guilty of a Sin, in giving them a juſt ground of keeping themſelves ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate from us; or they, in keeping themſelves ſo ſeparate without any juſt ground for it. But if, after all, our Author will not allow the word <hi>Sch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſm</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:37665:9"/> to be a term proper enough to denote ſuch <hi>a State of Separation;</hi> I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented that he ſhould put what other word he pleaſes in the room of it, as long as the thing intended is ſufficiently plain, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuch a State of Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration neceſſarily implies a Sin in one or other of the Parties.</p>
            <p>For the clearer diſcovering at whoſe door the Sin of this Schiſm which is between us lies, I have in my <hi>Addreſs</hi> propoſed ſeveral things to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: Againſt the <hi>manner</hi> of which, firſt, our Author takes this exception, that I <hi>rather Catechize the Non-Conformiſts by asking them Queſtions, than con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince them by Reaſons,</hi> pag. 97. To which I Anſwer, that there is not any Queſtion put in my whole Addreſs, but what, I think, as plainly carries in it the force of an aſſertion, as if I had ſet it down, not in an interroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but a prepoſition. Nor have I there delivered or ſuggeſted any aſſertion but what I have given or ſufficiently intimated my reaſon for, except the thing were ſo evident as to need no proof. But yet, to take away all pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Cavill, I ſhall in this <hi>Defence</hi> reduce my Queſtions into ſuch Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions as are naturally implyed in them; and fairly examine which are ſtrongeſt, my Reaſons for them, or his againſt them.</p>
            <p>The firſt Propoſition then which, on this occaſion, I have advanced (tho' under the form of a Queſtion) is, that <hi>in the Communion of our Church there is nothing wanting which is neceſſary to the Salvation of a Chriſtian:</hi> And as I have conſtantly ſerved <hi>my Cure</hi> in my own Perſon. (Notwitſtanding our Authors uncharitable Inſinuation to the contrary, <hi>pag.</hi> 98.) So have I in my <hi>Addreſs</hi> ſuggeſted ſuch proof of this aſſertion, as not to ſtand in need of him for my Curate or <hi>Delegate</hi> to prove it for me, <hi>viz. Becauſe our Church Teaches all the Fundamental Articles of the Chriſtian Faith, requires all Men to lead Vertuous and Holy Lives, and omits no part of Chriſt's Inſtitution, either in Baptiſm or the Lord's-Supper; which things are all that are required, as of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, to any Mans Salvation.</hi> Nor did I think it proper to offer any further Confirmation of theſe things, beſides the notoriety of them; becauſe I was not Diſputing with <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Pagans;</hi> to whom our Auther tell us <hi>Chriſt and his Apoſtles proved their Doctrines;</hi> But with the <hi>Non-Conformiſts,</hi> who do not deny what I have hitherto aſſerted (as the others did the Doctrines of the Goſpel) but give other Reaſons altogether for their ſeparation from us: And therefore why our Author would have me ſtand to prove theſe Points, before they are gainſaid, I know not; except it may be to divert the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from attending unto that which is the knot and difficulty of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſy; if any real difficulty at all there be in ſo very plain and evident a Caſe.</p>
            <p>Where an aſſertion is laid down in any Controverſy, there can be but two ways of returning an Anſwer to it, <hi>viz.</hi> either firſt, to deny the Truth of it; or ſecondly, to ſhew that tho' it may be true, yet is it impertinent to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37665:9"/> the purpoſe for which it is alleged. The former of theſe, our Author, I ſuppoſe, knows he cannot do in relation to the above-mentioned <hi>Propoſition.</hi> (Altho', according to his way, he ſeems to <hi>ſuggeſt</hi> ſomething like it, by urging me to undertake the proof of it. For the only reaſon why a man ſhould produce his Arguments to prove a thing, is becauſe it may be denied or doubted of.) But in order to the latter, without diſtinguiſhing between the caſe of our Church, and that of <hi>Rome,</hi> he produces, <hi>pag.</hi> 99. a paſſage of <hi>the Learned Chillingworth,</hi> which tho' levelled by its Author only againſt the Roman Church, yet, he ſets down as equally applicable againſt that Church alſo of which Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> himſelf was a Member; And that without taking any care to caution his own Party againſt an unjuſt and falſe Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that ſome of them have ſeemed to be inclined to; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s if the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> and the Eſtabliſh't Church were in a manner equally culpable. The ſubſtance of what he recites out of Mr. <hi>Chillinwarth,</hi> is compriſed in the firſt words of the Quotation it ſelf; <hi>All,</hi> ſays he, <hi>that we forſake in you is the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, Profeſſion and Practice of your Errors, &amp;c.</hi> Let but theſe <hi>Errors</hi> be taken away, and in all the reſt we ſhall agree very well. In Anſwer whereunto, I grant with that Learned man, in what follows, That <hi>to believe an Error, knowing it to be an Error, is abſolutely impoſſible; and for a man to profeſs what he does not believe, is Hypocritical and Sinful;</hi> and therefore ever to be avoided. But altho' this bears cloſe upon the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> which requires the Belief and Profeſſion of divers things, which from plain Scripture and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon we abundantly prove to be falſe; yet is it altogether wide from our caſe, except our Author had plainly told us (as we do the Papiſts) <hi>what thoſe Errors or falſe Doctrines are, the Belief or Profeſſion of which we require among the Conditions of our Communion:</hi> Which till he undertakes to do, he muſt, I think, acknowledge that what Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> ſays, as to the <hi>Believing</hi> and <hi>Profeſſing</hi> of Errors, is no way to his preſent purpoſe, except it be to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſe and keep up the prejudice of his own Party againſt us.</p>
            <p>But that Learned man excepts againſt <hi>Practiſing,</hi> as well as againſt <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving</hi> or <hi>Profeſſing</hi> of Errors. Now if by <hi>Practiſing an Error</hi> be meant the doing any thing which is contrary to God's Law; ſuch as praying to Saints, or worſhipping the Hoſt or Images, to which, and ſuch like things, undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly he had an Eye In that Expreſſion; I grant that it is a cauſe abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſufficient to refuſe the Communion of any Church, if ſhe requires any ſuch <hi>Practice</hi> as a Condition of it: But then it muſt be ſhewn that ſome ſuch Practice is ſo required by our Church, or elſe this Clauſe will be as little to the purpoſe as the former. But if by <hi>Practiſing an Error</hi> be meant the doing of a thing which is not Sinful, but yet is apprehended to be improper o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inconvenient; and therefore may be accounted an Error in Point, not o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> lawfulneſs, but of prudence, decency or the like; If any Church requires
<pb facs="tcp:37665:10"/> the practice only of ſuch an Error as this; however it may be proper to deſire, and with a modeſt earneſtneſs to preſs for an alteration in ſuch things for the better, yet I cannot ſee how upon this ground it can be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified to renounce or refuſe the Communion of ſuch a Church: But of this, anon.</p>
            <p>As to Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi>'s Propoſal to the Papiſts, that he was ready to join with them in any ſuch <hi>Form of Worſhipping God,</hi> as ſhould be <hi>wholly taken out of the Scriptures.</hi> If the ſame be made to us; I Anſwer, that if by <hi>a Form of Worſhip wholly taken out of the Scriptures</hi> be meant ſuch an one, every of whoſe <hi>Words</hi> and <hi>Expreſſions</hi> are immediately and in terms contained in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; the thing is hardly practicable: For as it is poſſible that the very Words and Phraſes of Scripture may be ſo joined and put together, as to wreſt and pervert the ſenſe and meaning thereof, which might eaſily occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion new Diſputes: So I believe will it be very difficult (nor certainly is it neceſſary) for any Church ſo to contrive all her Forms of Worſhip, as to uſe no word or action in any of them: but what is expreſsly contained in or preſcribed by the Scripture. But if ſuch a Form be meant, which, for ſubſtance, is wholly taken from the Scripture, and has nothing, either in its concomitant actions or expreſſions, which is contrary to the Scripture; which I believe was all that Learned man intended; I accept the propoſal; and offer our Liturgy as ſuch a Form of worſhip (as undoubtedly Mr. <hi>Chilling<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> judged it to be, or elſe he would not have conformed to it). And if then our Author cannot ſhew that there is ſomething therein contained, and thereby required, which is contrary to the holy Scriptures; he muſt, I think, by his own Confeſſion, be judged guilty of Schiſm, for refuſing to join with us in the uſe of it.</p>
            <p>The ſecond propoſition which in my Addreſs I offer (and that alſo couched under a Queſtion) is that <hi>nothing which is Sinful is required by us from thoſe who communicate with us.</hi> For which I there offer this as my reaſon, namely, <hi>becauſe none of our conſtitutions are forbidden by the Law of God, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be a Sin but what is ſo forbidden.</hi> To this he Anſwers, <hi>pag.</hi> 100. that there are ſuch things required by our Church as <hi>to them</hi> are ſinful; and ſome of our conſtitutions which <hi>to them do appear</hi> to be contrary to God's Law. For the proof of which he lays down, <hi>p.</hi> 101 a diſtinction, rational indeed in it ſelf, but here, I think not rightly applyed, namely that <hi>things are forbidden either expreſsly, or by iuſt and neceſſary conſequence.</hi> That ſome of our conſtitutions then, tho' not <hi>expreſsly,</hi> are yet <hi>by good conſequence forbidden,</hi> he endeavours to prove, becauſe <hi>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng not commanded by God, they are yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired by men, as parts or means of the Worſhip of God.</hi> Which as he pretends is contrary to the Word of God; and, for the proof of what he ſays, he produces ſome Texts of Scripture, and then confirms all by the Authority
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37665:10"/> of my Lord <hi>Biſhop of Derry,</hi> in his late <hi>Diſcourſe of Humane Inventi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that Paragraph of my <hi>Addreſs,</hi> now under conſideration, I had called thoſe Rites and Ceremonies, which by Authority are appointed to be uſed, by the name of <hi>Circumſtances of God's Worſhip;</hi> and as ſuch aſſerted the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of them. Now whereas he would prove the unlawfulneſs of theſe things as being required, <hi>not as Circumſtances, but as parts and means of the Worſhip of God:</hi> He ought very clearly and diſtinctly to have told us what he meant by a <hi>Circumſtance,</hi> what by a <hi>Part,</hi> and what by the <hi>Means</hi> of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and how theſe are diſtinguiſhed one from another: For as long as theſe terms, in which he ſeems to place the knot of the Controverſy, remain obſcure, it is not poſſible to clear the Diſpute, or rightly to apply the proofs which he brings: And yet without any explication o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> theſe terms, or ſhewing wherein the things ſignified by them do differ one from another, he proceeds to prove, <hi>pag.</hi> 102, that our Rites and Ceremonies are with us both <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Means of God's Worſhip.</hi> But that we may not be like men who are ſcuffling in the dark, and not diſtinctly knowing what it is we contend about; I muſt, as I proceed, endeavour to do what he has thought fit to leave undone; I mean to ſtate the ſignification of theſe words, that thereby we may know the difference of the things one from another.</p>
            <p>(It being then premiſed, what all, I ſuppoſe, will grant, that the true Worſhip of God conſiſts in thoſe things, and in thoſe only, which he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf has commanded) That (and nothing elſe but that) is properly to be called <hi>a Part</hi> of any thing, without which the <hi>thing</hi> would be in <hi>it ſelf</hi> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect and defective. Thus every Limb of a Man is a <hi>Part</hi> of him, becauſe the want of any of them would be a defect in the Man himſelf: But his garment, tho' a decent ornament, is yet no part of him, becauſe if he were ſtript ſtark naked, or cloathed in an undecent garb, tho' this might perhaps expoſe him to the ſcorn of ſome men; yet would he <hi>in himſelf</hi> be never the leſs a perfect and compleat man upon that account. Thus alſo Prayer, Thankſgiving, Conſeſſion, the Suſception of Baptiſm, and the receiving the Lord's-Supper, are each of them <hi>Parts</hi> of God's Worſhip; becauſe he who omits any one of them, in its proper ſeaſon, thereby renders his Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> defective and imperfect. But the outward Modes or Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, which may be annexed to this Worſhip or any part of it, are not themſelves any part of the Worſhip (altho' they may be a decent ornament of it) becauſe the abſence of them (altho' it might perhaps, in ſome mens eyes, render the Worſhip mean and contemptible, yet) would not make it, <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> to be ever the leſs compleat, perfect, or acceptable to Almighty God. If then our Author can prove, that it is the Judgment of our Church
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:37665:11"/> that the laying aſide of any of her Ceremonies would render the Worſhip of God, <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> imperfect or defective then, and not till then, he may truly lay it to her charge that ſhe requires theſe Ceremonies <hi>as a part of God's Worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>the Liturgy,</hi> ſays he, <hi>is a pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of the Worſhip of God, and theſe Ceremonies are a part of the Liturgy, therefore,</hi> &amp;c. I anſwer, that the <hi>ſubſtance and purport</hi> of our Liturgy, <hi>viz.</hi> Conſeſſion, Prayer, Thankſgiving, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are indeed <hi>parts</hi> of the Worſhip of God; for without any one of them the Worſhip would be imperfect: But the particular words, in which theſe Devotions are there expreſt, and the concomitant Ceremonies which are preſcribed to be uſed, are not, nor ever were, by our Church eſteemed <hi>as parts of Worſhip;</hi> but only as the <hi>Modes, Regulations</hi> and <hi>Method</hi> of it, alterable in themſelves by humane authority, and variable in divers particular Churches, without making thereby any alteration or variation in the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of the Worſhip. Altho' therefore, our Author's proofs, as he has managed them, are but very lame; yet becauſe the thing is true, I freel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> grant, that to require any thing <hi>as a part of God's Worſhip,</hi> which he himſelf has not commanded, is utterly unlawful; But then it is moſt evident from what I have ſaid, that our Liturgy or Ceremonies are no way concerned herein.</p>
            <p>Well, but if they are not to be eſteemed as <hi>parts,</hi> yet he will prove that they are required as <hi>means</hi> of the Worſhip of God, which is altogether as bad. Let us therefore enquire into the ſenſe and ſignification of this word alſo.</p>
            <p>To explain this word <hi>means,</hi> he adds, <hi>p.</hi> 102, the word <hi>ways</hi> to it; and tells us that our Liturgy and Ceremonies <hi>are reputed ways and means of the Worſhip</hi> of God: Now the <hi>way</hi> of doing a thing always denotes, not directly the action it ſelf, but the <hi>method</hi> and <hi>manner</hi> of performing it; one and the ſame action for ſubſtance, being often capable of being performed after <hi>divers ways</hi> or manners. I agree with him therefore that our Liturgy and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies are to us, as the Directory to him, the <hi>way, means</hi> or <hi>method</hi> of our publick Worſhip of God: But yet the premiſſes out of which he infers this concluſion, are ſo crude and confuſed, that they are by no means to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into diſcourſe, much leſs granted as truth, until their meaning be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctly cleared, <hi>viz. becauſe,</hi> ſays he, <hi>no ſolemn publick Worſhip can be perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, nor Sacraments adminiſtred without them:</hi> By which if he means that our Church has ſuch an opinion of her Liturgy and Ceremonies, as to think it impoſſible, <hi>in it ſelf,</hi> rightly to Worſhip God or adminiſter the Sacraments without them; it is notoriouſly falſe: But if he means no more than this, namely, that we judge that every man, who is ſubject to the authority of the law of the Land, is bound in Conſcience always to perform the publick Worſhip of God, and Celebration of the Sacraments, according to that manner pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in our Liturgy; this obligation ariſing not from the <hi>nature</hi> of the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:37665:11"/> particular Forms and Ceremonies there enjoyned, nor from any <hi>particular</hi> command of God appointing them; but only from the general Law of God, which requires Obedience to be paid to our lawful Superiors, and from the Laws of the Land conſequent thereto; and therefore laſting no longer than ſuch Laws of the Land ſhall remain in force: If this, I ſay, be all he means, we grant it, and are ready to juſtifie our Judgment in this matter.</p>
            <p>But here he preſſes me with a great abſurdity as he thinks; <hi>If all Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ſhould refuſe to ſay Common-Prayer or adminiſter the Sacraments, with all theſe Ceremonies, then, according to the Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, it would be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful to Woſhip God publickly in this Kingdom.</hi> Now if he would infer from hence, that therefore our Liturgy ought to be aboliſhed; by the ſame reaſon it will follow, that no Law whatſoever muſt any where be made for the Regulating the Worſhip of God, or adminiſtration o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raments. For if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll Miniſters ſhould refuſe to celebrate the publick Worſhip, and adminiſter the Sacraments according to that Law; then, according to that Law, it would be unlawful to Worſhip God publickly in that Kingdom or Common-wealth where any ſuch Law ſhould be Enacted. A conſequence fit only for ſuch wild Sectaries as would reject all rules of order and decency, and follow their own extravagant fancies only in maettrs of Religion and the Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>But let us for once put this mad ſuppoſition with him <hi>that all Miniſters ſhould refuſe to officiate according to our Liturgy:</hi> What would be the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence? or what muſt be done in ſuch a caſe? I anſwer if ſuch a refuſal ſhould proceed from wilfulneſs, it would be a great ſin in the Miniſters that refuſed; but if from want of information or due apprehenſion, it would only be a ſin of Ignorance, and therefore more eaſily pardonable before God. But in ſuch an extraordinary caſe, the neceſſity of things would probably put the Government upon ſome ſpeedy Reſolution, either of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding other Miniſters, if all thoſe lately in office ſhould, on a ſuddain, loſe their Wits; or elſe of altering their Eccleſiaſtical Laws, in condeſcenſion to the infirmity of their Miniſters, rather than the publick Worſhip of God and adminiſtration of the Sacraments ſhould ceaſe among them.</p>
            <p>But becauſe I call the Ceremonies preſcribed by our Liturgy <hi>circumſtances in the worſhip of God,</hi> which he will not allow that they are; it will not be amiſs to explain what is meant by the word <hi>circumſtance.</hi> Whatſoever then is a means or concomitant of any action, but no <hi>part</hi> of the action it ſelf; that I call (and ſo I thing do all People) a circumſtance of it. Thus for example: To travel from <hi>Dubl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> to <hi>Drog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eda</hi> is an action; but to go either on foot, or on horſeback, or in a coach, to wear a cloak and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> wear them, and the like, are only <hi>circumſtances</hi> of this Journey: for a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is ſaid never the more or the leſs to travel, whatever convenienci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:37665:12"/> have or want for the performance of his Journey. Thus alſo to Worſhip God is an action; but to perform this Service either by a Printed Form of Words, or by no ſet Form at all, to wear a black or a white garment, to kneel or to ſtand at the time of doing it, and ſuch like things, are no more but <hi>circumſtances</hi> of this Worſhip; becauſe a man may truly and acceptably Worſhip God in any of theſe ways, if the ſubſtance of his Worſhip be right, and his heart be rightly diſpoſed (altho', for decency ſake, it is very ſit that in a Congregation there ſhould be ſome ſettled Uniformity in theſe things), and an aggregate of theſe circumſtances taken together, is what is uſually called the <hi>way</hi> of doing a thing. Thus if it be asked which way (I do not mean by what road, but in what manner) did ſuch a man travel to <hi>Drogheda?</hi> It may properly be anſwered, he went on foot, with a coat to keep him from the rain and cold, and carried his proviſion with him; or he went on horſeback, or in a coach, and had ſuch and ſuch conveniencies for his Journey. Thus alſo if we were inquiring after the Worſhip of any Church or Party whatſoever, the natural order of our Queſtions would be this: Firſt to ask whom they Worſhipped? <hi>viz.</hi> whether the true God or a falſe God, or any other Perſon beſides God: And if it appeared that they Worſhipped the true God, then the ſecond thing to be asked would be wherein does that Worſhip which they pay to God conſiſt? Do they confeſs their Sins, and Pray to him, and give him Thanks? Are they Baptized, and do they celebrate the Lord's Supper according to God's own command? And if we ſhould find that in all this they followed the rule of God's word; then in the third place this Queſtion would fall in, <hi>viz.</hi> After what <hi>way</hi> and manner, or by what means, or in what method, do they pay and perform this Worſhip? What time, what place, what words, what geſtures, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do they appoint or uſe in the ſeveral parts of it.</p>
            <p>Thus far then our Author and I are agreed, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, That to preſcribe any thing <hi>as a part of God's Worſhip</hi> which he himſelf has not commanded, is a ſin. But then I have ſhewn that our Forms and Ceremonies are not by us made <hi>ſuch parts</hi> of the Worſhip of God. Secondly, I agree with him, that our Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy and Ceremonies are the <hi>way, means</hi> or method of performing our publick Devotions: But then I have alſo ſhewn that this ſignifies no more but that theſe things, which are thus by humane Law preſcribed, are the <hi>circumstances</hi> which do accompany and regulate the <hi>manner</hi> of our Worſhip. Now if our Author's proofs do evince, that to require any thing, which God himſelf has not commanded, as a <hi>way or means</hi> of Worſhip, renders the thing it ſelf unlawful, and in effect forbiden, without any other prohibition of it; then I muſt confeſs he has not only ſufficiently anſwered my <hi>Addreſs to the Non-Conformiſts,</hi> but alſo over-turned all the Liturgies and Rituals, not of our Church only, but of all other Churches alſo: Nay, I do not well ſee how
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:37665:12"/> the Directory it ſelf will eſcape the ſtroke of ſo ſtrict a Cenſure; except he were able to ſhew, that every Punctilio which is there preſcribed, is no more than what is (I muſt not ſay allowed and left at liberty but) poſitively commanded by God.</p>
            <p>And as thoſe Arguments, upon the ſtrength of which we renounce the Communion of any Church, and refuſe Obedience to the Law of the Land, ought to be both very clear and very ſolid; ſo, that I may not abate the force of thoſe which our Author brings, I ſhall ſet them down in his own words, without omitting a ſyllable.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt then,</hi> ſays he p. 101. <hi>whatever [part or] means of divine Worſhip is not commanded, is forbidden, is evident from that reaſon given</hi> Lev. 10. 1. <hi>why God deſtroyed</hi> Nadab <hi>and</hi> Abihu, <hi>for offering ſtrange fire; which is this: For I commanded them not.</hi> Now (beſides that he perverts the Text by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the word <hi>for</hi> to make the words run in an argumentative Style, which are only part of an Hiſtorical Narration; and by putting the word <hi>I</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>he,</hi> as if thoſe words were immediately ſpoken by God himſelf, whereas they are only a part of that Relation which <hi>Moſes</hi> makes of the matter of fact). The Caſe of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> was plainly this: God had commanded that when Incenſe was to be burnt before him, it ſhould be done with Fire <hi>taken from off the Altar,</hi> as appears from <hi>Lev.</hi> 16. 12. But theſe men, neglecting the Command of God, put other <hi>Strange</hi> Fire into their Cenſers; for which they were deſtroyed by <hi>Fire from the Lord.</hi> Lev. 10. 1, 2. All then that can be inferred from hence, is, that whoſoever ſhall omit to do what God Commands, as <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> did, to take Fire from the Altar; and <hi>inſtead thereof,</hi> ſhall do another thing which God has not commanded, as they did in putting ſtrange Fire in their Cenſers; is guilty of a ſin: But where nothing is omitted which God has command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it does not follow from hence, that the doing of any thing which is uncommanded, in the Worſhip of God, is therefore unlawful, becauſe it is not commanded. But if he ſhall tell me that the Command for taking fire from the Altar was not given, for ought that appears, till after the death of <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu;</hi> I ſhall deſire him to let me know, if there were no certain ſort of Fire at that time ordained and appointed for the burning of Incenſe; how could that Fire which theſe men offered be termed <hi>Strange Fire?</hi> For the word <hi>Strange</hi> neceſſarily implys that there was ſome other Fire which was <hi>not Strange,</hi> which they ought to have offered, that is to ſay, ſome certain ſort of Fire particularly appointed for this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>His next Argument is this. <hi>The reaſon,</hi> ſays he, <hi>of Gods rejecting what was offered,</hi> Iſ. 1. 12. <hi>is given; Who hath required theſe things at your hands.</hi> To which I anſwer, that the things there ſpoken of, and which God at that time rejected, were ſuch as he had poſitively commanded and <hi>required</hi>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:37665:13"/> from the people of Iſrael; namely, <hi>Sacrifices, burnt-Offerings, Incenſe,</hi> &amp;c. as every man that reads the precedent and following Verſes may plainly ſee. The reaſon then why God rejected them could not be, as our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor would inſinuate, becauſe he had not <hi>required</hi> them (for 'tis plain that he had required them in the Moſaick Law). But becauſe the People reſted in theſe outward performances; and were not truly ſanctified in their hearts, nor holy in their lives, which was what he chiefly, and ſo in a manner <hi>only,</hi> required from them, as in compariſon thereof almoſt not to regard thoſe outward Performances, altho' of his own appointment. That this is the plain and only purport of that place, appears ſo evidently from the Context and whole deſign of that Chapter, that it is not to be imagined how any man could miſtake it, except he did it wilfully: And all that can be inferred from this whole Paſſage, is, that outward Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, altho' of God's own Appointment; are yet of no eſteem with him, if they are not accompanied with true Holineſs of Mind and Actions. Which how it can be applied to our preſent Controverſy, I am at a loſs to find.</p>
            <p>His next Argument is this, <hi>The cauſe of God's Judgments on falſe Prophets</hi> Jer. 14, 14, 15. <hi>is, I ſent them not, neither have I commanded them.</hi> Now obſerve the Conſequence: God Almighty denounces a heavy Judgment upon thoſe pretended Prophets, who, being <hi>not ſent nor commanded</hi> by him, did yet preſume, not only to tell <hi>Lyes,</hi> but alſo to <hi>Propheſy</hi> them <hi>in his Name,</hi> which was a moſt abominable Sin; and from hence our Author would infer that therefore whatſoever is not commanded in the Worſhip of God, is forbidded to be uſed, as a way or means of it. But how this Inference, or any thing like it, can be juſtified, I know not.</p>
            <p>His laſt Argument is this; <hi>Fear or Worſhip of God taught by the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Men is not only vain,</hi> Matth. 15. 9. <hi>but brings Plagues on them who abuſe their wiſdom that way.</hi> Iſ. 29. 14. Where tho' he very crudely and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſtinctly repreſents the meaning of the former of theſe two Texts which he alleges; yet I freely grant the truth of what he aſſerts, if the thing be rightly underſtood. But where the fear of God proceeds from an awful ſenſe of his Greatneſs and Majeſty; and the Worſhip of God is ſuch as he himſelf has taught and preſcribed; conſiſting in Confeſſion, Prayer, Thankſgiving, and the Celebration of Baptiſm and the Lord's Supper, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out omitting any thing which is of divine inſtitution; And Men are taught and urged thus to Fear and Worſhip God, becauſe God himſelf has com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them ſo to do; And the Law of the Land (which may be termed the <hi>Commandment of Alan)</hi> interpoſes no farther, but only to enforce, and not to alter, the Law of God, and to ſettle and regulate the outward Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of this Worſhip; which the Law of God has not determined; I cannot ſee what from either of theſe Texts can with any colour be object<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:37665:13"/> againſt ſuch a conſtitution of things as this; except it be where pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, and not ſober and impartial reaſon, is the Interpreter of them.</p>
            <p>To ſtrengthen theſe his proofs from Scripture (which of themſelves I am ſure are very weak) our Author adds, that <hi>we are lately taught</hi> what he has aſſerted, <hi>to be the Doctrine of the Eſtabliſhed Church, by the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhop of</hi> Derry, <hi>in his Vanity of Humane Inventions.</hi> And after having recited ſome of His Lordſhip's words out of the Introduction of the Book mentioned; he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes thus: <hi>Now, if Croſs, Ring,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be not expr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſly contained in Scripture, or warranted by the Examples of holy Men therein, they muſt, according to the Biſhop of</hi> Derry's <hi>reaſoning, be diſpleaſing to God, and ſo forbidden by him.</hi> p. 101, 102. But here ſure our Author cannot but know that he is guilty, in a moſt palpable manner of a double piece of diſingenuity. For neither does my Lord Biſhop of <hi>Derry</hi> there <hi>teach</hi> us that what is contained in thoſe words is the <hi>Doctrine of the eſtabliſhed Church,</hi> but only offers his own judgment of thoſe things, as being highly reaſonable; nor does our Author faithfully recite what his Lordſhip has ſaid; but omits part of the laſt Sentence, without which it is not poſſible fully to underſtand the meaning and deſign of that Paragraph. His Lordſhips Concluſion is this, <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce God has vouchſaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d us a certain Direction, or his Worſhip in the holy Scriptures; it is to be ſuppoſed that all ways of Worſhip are diſpleaſing to him that are not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly contained, or warranted by Examples of holy Men mentioned therein;</hi> OR MAY NOT BE DEDUCED BY PLAIN CONSEQUENCE, OR BY PARTTY OF REASON FROM THEM (which laſt words our Author has very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairly left out) ſo that altho' our Ceremonies <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſly contained in the Scriptures, or warranted,</hi> in particular, <hi>by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xamp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oly Men therein;</hi> Yet ſtill, according to my Lord Biſhop of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, (in that very Paragraph which our Author quotes) <hi>they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to God, if they can be deduced by plain Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>rce, or by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And that all our Forms and Ceremonies are juſtified by plain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or an evident congruity and <hi>parity of Reaſon.</hi> either from the Rules or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>amples of holy Men in Scripture, is what his Lordſhip has partly proved in the Seq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l of that Book, and may very e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ectually be made good touching thoſe other things of which he has not there had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ccaſion to ſpeak.</p>
            <p>From what our Author has hitherto been diſcourſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, he p. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2. inſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs an Anſwer to this Queſtion which I had put, viz. <hi>Can a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y thing be called a Sin which God has not ſorbid?</hi> And he tells me, <hi>It may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s he, <hi>uncommanded Worſhip is Sin.</hi> Now ſee how an ill cauſe runs a man into Perplexities and Contradictions: He had juſt before been proving that <hi>uncommanded Worſhip is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rbidden;</hi> and, yet, almoſt in the ſame breath he gives it as an Inſtance of a thing that is a Sin, altho' it be <hi>not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> But altho' I have already granted that the uſe of any <hi>uncommanded</hi> thing, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:37665:14"/> 
               <hi>part of God's Worſhip,</hi> is unlawful (and the only reaſon why it is ſo, is, becauſe it is forbidden) yet neither does it follow from hence, nor has our Author pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that <hi>uncommanded Circumſtances of Worſhip are ſinful:</hi> And upon a Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition that they were ſinful; yet upon what other account they could be ſo beſides their being forbidden, I ſhould be very glad to learn from him.</p>
            <p>But he gives another Inſtance. <hi>To Baptize,</hi> ſays he, <hi>without the Sign of the Croſs, Communicate without Kneeling,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>are not forbidden of God, and yet the Eſtabliſhed Church account theſe Sins.</hi> To which the Anſwer is very eaſy, <hi>viz.</hi> That the Eſtabliſhed Church accounts theſe things to be no farther Sins than <hi>as they are forbidden by God.</hi> Diſobedience to lawful Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, in ſuch things as are in themſelves lawful, is moſt certainly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, ſince then the Croſs after Baptiſm, Kneeling at the Communion, &amp;c. are in themſelves lawful, and commanded by lawful Authority; For any man, <hi>wilfully,</hi> to omit any of theſe Circumſtances, in the perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of theſe Offices, as long as the Laws for them do ſtand in force, is an Act of Diſobedience to the higher Powers; and, upon this account, and no other, is reckoned as a Sin by us.</p>
            <p>But, <hi>Nonconformity,</hi> with us, <hi>is puniſhed more ſeverely than ſome groſs Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moralities!</hi> I anſwer, that tho' this were true, yet makes it nothing to our preſent Controverſy; nor can it any way be proved from thence, that Conformity is unlawful; and therefore, for what purpoſe this is here mentioned, except it be to raiſe the paſſion, and thereby more effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually to cloud the reaſon, of his own Party, I cannot imagine. What ever errors there may be in the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of a Church (as no Humane Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution perhaps was ever throughly perfect) if ſome part of it be too ſtrict, and other too looſe; or whatever elſe the fault may be; I think it is the Duty of every good Chriſtian, fairly to repreſent ſuch things to thoſe who are in Authority, that they may in a due manner be rectiſied. But as ſuch defects as theſe, are no juſt ground to refuſe the Communion of any Church whatſoever; ſo to upbraid her with them upon an improper occaſion; and when ſuch a reproach makes nothing to the Argument in hand; in my apprehenſion, ſeems not altogether agreeable to the true Chriſtian ſpirit of meekneſs and Charity.</p>
            <p>That this hint then which he here gives is not to the direct pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of our preſent Diſpute, is moſt plain. But what if, after he has af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it ſo poſitively, and that too with an Aſſeveration, it ſhould not appear to be ſo clear and evident a truth as he ſuppoſes it. He tells us, that <hi>for Nonconformity Men are to be Excommunicated, Ipſo ſacto, But not for ſome groſs Immoralities.</hi> Now beſides that the <hi>Ipſo ſacto,</hi> upon which he lays ſuch a Streſs, is wanting in theſe Canons of the Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> which are made concerning this matter (which is enough to render his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:37665:14"/> Allegation falſe, becauſe our preſent controverſy is confined within the bounds of this Kingdom). Let him but conſult the ſecond and third Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphs of the Rubrick, which is placed immediately before our Communion Service, and there he ſhall find that <hi>notorious evil livers,</hi> who are the ſame with thoſe who are guilty of <hi>groſs immoralities,</hi> are to be excluded from the Holy Communion; and an <hi>account</hi> of them to be forthwith <hi>given to the Ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ary, who is to proceed againſt</hi> ſuch Perſons, <hi>according to Canon;</hi> which I think is much the ſame thing with an Excommunication <hi>ipſo facto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, it may be, I ſhall be told that tho' our Eccleſiaſtical Laws may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps be found to be equally ſevere againſt immorality and Nonconformity, yet we do not find that the former has been ſo ſtrictly puniſhed amongſt us as the latter. To which I anſwer, that if this were true it may be indeed juſtly accounted as a great fault in thoſe whoſe Office it was to put thoſe Laws in Execution; but ought not to be charged upon the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Church it ſelf. And, beſides this, it is not ſo eaſy a matter legally to puniſh many immoralities, as at the firſt one would be apt to think. For without ſufficient proof, puniſhment ought not to be inflicted; and not only are People generally very unwilling to appear, as witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt others in ſuch caſes as theſe; But Men alſo do commonly take care, ſo far to hide their Act, of wickedneſs, as to make it very difficult to produce any legal proof of ſuch things againſt them, altho' at the ſame time they may labour under great ſuſpicion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> much Scandal upon that account: Which I take to be the great cauſe why ſometimes the beſt of Men, when they have been in Authority, have not been able, with all their care and diligence, to ſuppreſs vice, as both the Laws have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir own inclinations led them. To conclude this digreſſion: As every honeſt Man ought ſincerely to deſire and heartily to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his endeavours th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t true piety may be promoted, and all wickedneſs ſuppreſſed; ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for my part am fully of opi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion that no ſober and peaceable Man ſhould at all be puniſhed, on account of the miſtakes of his Conſcience, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or which re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon I am altogether <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or having the penalty of our Laws againſt Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity wholly relaxed: Which yet I think ought to be done with that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>utions prudence, as that all publick diſturbances, both now and hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, may, as much as is poſſible, be prevented; And, under the pretence of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> tender Conſciences, a fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e liberty ought not to be given to every one at pleaſure <hi>who want only to inſult and trample upon a legal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſhment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Author proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eds and tells us that <hi>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le, Salt, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m, Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>le, &amp;c. are no more forbidden than the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n of the Croſs: Why then</hi> ſays he <hi>hath the Church rejected them?</hi> To which the Church has long ſince given a clear and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory anſwer, in a ſhort diſcourſe pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fixt to the Book of Common Prayer; which bears this Title <hi>Of Ceremo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> why ſome be aboliſhed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eme reta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ned;</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:37665:15"/> with which if he were not ſatisfied, he ought to have made his exceptions againſt it, before he had again renewed the Queſtion. But <hi>the ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are uſed by the Papiſts for all their Ceremonies;</hi> I anſwer if the Arguments are bad, let him refuſe them; But if not, why are they the worſe becauſe the Papiſts make uſe of them? And as the Papiſts, to run down Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, do not ſcruple vigorouſly to plead the Cauſe of the <hi>Socinians;</hi> by rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Wits to ſhew that the Doctrine of the bleſſed <hi>Trinity</hi> is liable to as many and as great ſeeming abſurdities as that of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> ſo it ſeems ſome Nonconformiſts, in order to gain their point againſt the Eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed Church, do perform no mean picce of Service for the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in endeavouring to perſwade the World that the caſe of that Church and that of our Eſtabliſhed one, are very near of kin. But as I have already ſhewn that what our Author has quoted out of Mr. <hi>Chillingworth</hi> againſt them is no way to be applyed to us; ſo between their Ceremonies and ours, both as to the exceſſive number and great abuſe of them, there is ſuch extraordinary difference (as our Church takes notice in the place, but now quoted) that I wonder how any Ingenuous Man could offer to make a Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el between them. And as for what he adds in the Concluſion of this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, that, <hi>ſelling Doves and changing Money were not forbidden, yet Chriſt drove all out of the Temple;</hi> I anſwer, that thus to make a Market of that place which was dedicated and appropriated to the ſervice of God, was, if not in expreſs words, yet by very good conſequence, forbidden; As our Saviour ſhews, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21 13. Or if it were not forbidden, I deſire to know upon what account were they to be blamed, who there ſold Doves and chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Money. And let him but prove that any of our Ceremonies are equally forbidden, and I will renounce them. Or if he cannot do this; to what purpoſe is this inſtance given, except it be to keep up an unreaſonable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt our way of Worſhip?</p>
            <p>To vindicate our ſelves from the imputation of <hi>Superſtition</hi> in the <hi>uſe</hi> of Ceremonies, as well as our Ceremonies themſelves from that of <hi>unlawfulneſs,</hi> I took notice, in my Addreſs, that <hi>we have ſufficiently declared that we place no holineſs in them; but only uſe them as things in themſelves indifferent, ordained by authority for decency and order, and alterable at any time by the ſame au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</hi> From whence our Author, ſmartly, as he thinks, infers upon me, <hi>pag.</hi> 103. that <hi>if</hi> our Ceremonies <hi>be not holy, they are not civil, nor natural ones, and therefore muſt be propha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> But is not this meer trifling, thus to perplex a diſpute with variety of terms, without explaining and determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the ſenſe of them? For had he but laid down the definitions and diſtinctions of and belonging to theſe things this pretence would imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately appear to be vain and ridiculous, Whatever Ceremony is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anded by <hi>God</hi> to be uſed; as long as the obligation of that command
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:37665:15"/> laſts, may properly be called <hi>holy;</hi> whatſoever ſuch is commanded by <hi>the Law of the Land only,</hi> altho' to be uſed in the exerciſe of Religion, may, yet, if you pleaſe, be called <hi>a civil Ceremony.</hi> And, where the Chriſtian Religion is not upheld by the Civil Authority, whatſoever is appointed by <hi>the Church it ſelf</hi> may reaſonably be termed by the name of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical:</hi> And, to give no more inſtances, where bare <hi>cuſtom</hi> without any other inſtitution has introduced the practice of any ſuch thing; if there be nothing therein which is ſinful, why may it not bear the name of <hi>cuſtomary?</hi> From whence it will evidently appear that if either our Author's Logick or Charity had not been ſomething defective, he needed not ſo haſtily to have concluded our Ceremonies to be <hi>Prophane,</hi> becauſe we place no <hi>holin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs</hi> in them; but might have found out ſome other appellation for them. But ſince the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> of our Ceremonies has been ſo ſhamefully confuted; it may perhaps be a pretty new hint to give thoſe People who are diſaſfected to them, to tell them that we do in effect own them to be <hi>Profane,</hi> becauſe we place no <hi>holineſs in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſtill, ſays he, <hi>they cannot be free from Superſtition, if they are ſuperadded as parts of Worſhip!</hi> But I have ſhewn that they are <hi>not ſuperadded as parts of Worſhip:</hi> And if he had but enquired into the true notion of <hi>a part of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> as it is diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of it, he could not in modeſty have inſiſted upon ſuch a poor pretence.</p>
            <p>In the remaining part of this paragraph he offers three things more, by way of anſwer to what I had above affirmed. The firſt is, That <hi>tho' the nature of Ceremonies may, yet the uſe of them cannot be indifferent; becauſe the end of uſing them muſt be either good, evil, or impertinent, and our actions are ſpecified by their ends.</hi> Which is as much as to ſay, that to uſe indifferent Ceremonies for a good end, is a good action; to uſe them for an evil end, is an evil action; and to uſe them for an impertinent end, is an impertinent action: All which things I freely grant; and tho' ſomething may be inferred thereout in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of our Church; yet what they here ſerve for, except it be for amuſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and perplexity, I am not able to diſcover. Secondly, he tells us that <hi>things indifferent can make nothing decent or orderly; ſeeing they have nothing of decency or order in them; for if they had, they would be really good, and not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</hi> To which I anſwer that things indifferent, in their own nature, may yet contribute to the <hi>decency</hi> and <hi>order</hi> of a good action; not by any intrinſick goodneſs which is inherent in themſelves, but as they are <hi>ſigns of the good intention</hi> of the perſons who preſcribe and practiſe them in the performace of ſuch an action. Thus for Example, to bow the body, to kneel, to ſing, and that in a ſtinted metre are things in their nature indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent: For neither are they any neceſſary part of the Law of Nature, nor do we find that they were ever commanded by God, until pious and good
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:37665:16"/> men took up thoſe cuſtoms of themſelves in the Worſhip of God: And yet I believe our Author will not deny, but that theſe things may conduce to the more decent and orderly Performance of ſuch Worſhip, where they are ſincerely intended as outward marks of that inward Devotion and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence which men do truly pay to God. And why may not the ſame thing be ſaid of any other lawful Ceremonies or Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cumſtances, which are ſinc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ly intended and made uſe of to the very ſame purpoſe?</p>
            <p>But thirdly, he comes in with a dilemma; <hi>If,</hi> ſays he, <hi>theſe Ceremonies are neceſſary means of decency and order, then Chriſt and his Apoſtles, who uſed them not, baptized, prayed and communicated und<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cently. If not neceſſary, why is all this needleſs contention about them?</hi> To the firſt part of which argument I Anſwer, that our Church never pretended that theſe particular Ceremonies; were abſolutely neceſſary to order and decency: But only (as things ſtood at the time of the Reformation) highly convenient to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>etained; and, all things conſidered, not ſo convenient to be altered. But to the ſecond I reply more diſtinctly; Firſt, that to alter the whole frame of our Liturgy (as ſome would have it) would, in my apprehenſion, be a thing of very ill conſequence, as well upon the account of thoſe planſible pretences is would give the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> againſt us; (who would be ſure to make their advantage of it) as of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>candal it would give to a multitude of our own weaker members, who either having heard the manner of our Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip ſo often decryed by the Non-conformi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s as Popi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, Superſtitious, and even Idolat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ous: would be apt to think that all this accuſation was true, if all the things which were ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>lt with, ſhould wholly be laid aſide; or elſe perhaps would be much diſſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſied to have thoſe things aboliſhed, which to them do appear to be ſo orde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly and decent, and ſuch others ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted in the room thereof as would not be ſo well ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> to them. But ſecondly as for ſome Alterations and improvements which mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht, I think, be very well made in our conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iautions; I am altogether of opinion that no ſober and well meaning Man of our Church would be againſt them, if it d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d but any way appear that the Noncon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſls, or any member of them, would thereby be won to our Communion. But while they ſeem to demand all, or elſe will be ſatisfied with nothing; it is feared by many <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t even ſuch al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations as are out inconſiderable in themſelves, would yet be o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient conſeqa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce. But if our Governours ſhould be gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ted to be to blame in inſiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſtly upon things which are not neceſſary; Yet ſtill I do not ſee how this con be ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ded as a juſt excuſe for refuſing that obedience to them, which the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of the Land requires, and the law of God does <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot forbid. For there are caſes where tho' it may be a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ault in Legi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ors or Parents too ſtrictly to command, yet ſtill it would be the duty of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject or the Child to obey.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:37665:16"/>
            <p>In the next paragraph he grants, <hi>with me, that Worſhip cannot be perform<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> without Circumſtances, and that all outward Circumſtances of Worſhip are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsly preſcribed by God:</hi> From whence it demonſtratively follows, that ſame Circumſtance of Worſhip may be uſed (and therefore why not by lawful authority appointed and determined) which God himſelf has not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. What then can juſtly be ſaid agaiſt our Ceremonies, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have ſo evidently proved to be <hi>Circumſtances</hi> only, and not <hi>parts of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Why this, ſays our Author here, that they <hi>are myſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cal Rites and Cerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>not Circumſtances,</hi> which things, in his opinion, are very different; <hi>tho' craftily or ignorantly they be conſounded</hi> Now whether it may be our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's <hi>eraſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or <hi>ignorance,</hi> I know not; but this I am ſure of, that to lay ſuch a ſtreſs, as he does, upon hard words, without diſtinctly explaining their ſignification, is the way eternally to <hi>confound,</hi> and perplex all, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to determine any Diſputes or Controverſies: And therefore if he would have avoided that Cenſure which here obliquely he caſts upon us, he ſhould have deſined and carefully diſtinguiſhed thoſe things, which in his opinion, we <hi>conſound;</hi> and have told us particularly what was to be underſtood by a <hi>Myſtical Rite;</hi> and wherein it diſſered from a <hi>Circumſtance.</hi> And what thoſe ſame myſteries are, which he ſuppoſes to be comprehended under any of our Ceremonies. And laſtly, whether all ſuch myſteries are abſolutely unlawful; or if not, for what reaſon ours are ſo: For my part I know no other myſticalneſs in any or our Ceremonles, ſave only that we uſe them as apt and proper marks of what we inwardly intend: We uncover our heads, and kneel on our knees in the Worſhip of God, for no other reaſon, but to denote that profound Reverence which we ought always to have for his Majeſty; and ſomething of the like nature we deſign in all the reſt of our Ceremonies: And if he will call this a <hi>Myſtery;</hi> yet I think he ought c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> early to prove <hi>the thing to be unlawful.</hi> And not take it for a ſufficient contutation of us, that he has improperly applyed a hard word upon this occaſion, without any diſtinct explication of its meaning.</p>
            <p>But <hi>time, place, perſon, &amp;c. which are Circumſtances of humane actions cannot,</hi> ſays he, <hi>be called Rites or Ceremonies.</hi> I pray, why ſo? were not the <hi>time</hi> of the Jewiſh Sabbath, and other Feſtivals, the <hi>place Jeruſalem,</hi> and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> where they kept their Feaſts, and performed much of their Worſhip; And the <hi>perſons</hi> of the particular Tribe of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>evi,</hi> who were immediately appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to miniſter to God in their publick Service; were not the obſervation of all theſe, I ſay, parts of the Ceremonial Law of <hi>Moſes?</hi> And if they were, why may not the particular <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> and <hi>pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> appointed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of an action, be called Ceremonies of it as well as the <hi>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dy</hi> or the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in which the ſame is to be do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:37665:17"/>
            <p>But if <hi>Ceremony</hi> and <hi>Circumſtance</hi> do thus in a manner ſignifie the ſame thing, <hi>Ceremonies ſhould be neceſſary and not indifferent, ſeeing it is impoſsible to do any thing without Circumſtances!</hi> I Anſwer, That tho' to do an action <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Circumſtances</hi> be impoſſible, yet <hi>this or that particular Circumſtance</hi> may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indifferent, and not neceſſary; becauſe it may be changed for another: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd if we will be nice in diſtinguiſhing theſe words <hi>Ceremony</hi> and <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,</hi> one from the other; all the difference that I know between them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is, <hi>viz.</hi> That as every thing which is a concomitant of an action, is ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ily called a <hi>Circumſtance</hi> of it; ſo thoſe Circumſtances, which by any Law or Cuſtom generally obſerved, are particularly determined and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>exed to the performance of that action, are uſually termed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of it. And accordingly there may be Ceremonies of Divine, Civil, Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical, or b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re cuſtomary Determination and Appointment, as I have but now ſaid.</p>
            <p>But if a Ceremony in Worſhip, which I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rm to be but a Circumſtance, be <hi>not natural</hi> and <hi>neceſſary for a decent performance of the action,</hi> nor <hi>compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in any general Law of Chriſt;</hi> it muſt be an <hi>addition to his Inſtitutions, and contrary to that precept,</hi> Deut. 12. 32. But here again is a great ſtreſs laid upon doubtful expreſſions, without ſo much as one word offered toward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the meaning, and removing the ambiguity of them. For neither has he told us what he means by theſe words, <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary;</hi> which ſometimes are taken in a ſtrict Senſe, to denote ſuch things as are <hi>abſolutely and indiſpenſably required,</hi> or dictated by the meer inſtinct <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſometimes, in a larger Senſe, to ſignifie ſuch things as are only very proper and convenient: Nor has he informed us what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> by b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing <hi>Comprehended <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n a General Law of Chriſt:</hi> For <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g may be thus comprehended in a general Law, either <hi>immediately</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> (as every dire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t Act of Sin is comprehended under ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>hilition; and every poſitive and direct Act of Duty under ſome of the General Commands) or elſe more remotely and reductively, (as the <hi>means of performing a Duty, or reſiſting a Temptation,</hi> and alſo ſome of the moſt <hi>Congruous and proper Circumſtances of Action;</hi> which tho' variable in themſelves, according to the various caſes which fall out; yet accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the rules of Prudence and Congruity are often Reducible, tho' more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, and not ſo directly, to ſome of the general rules of Duty, becauſe from ſuch things as theſe the goodneſs of Actions may be enhan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> aggravated). Nor laſtly has he fixed the ſignification of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>An Addition to Chriſt's Inſtitutions:</hi> By which if he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the doing any thing more in the performance of a Duty, than what ſtrictly and ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ly Chriſt has Commanded; Either he muſt prove that Chriſt has Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded every <hi>Punc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="5 letters">
                     <desc>•••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of what is preſcribed in the Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:37665:17"/> or elſe he muſt condemn that as well as the Liturgy, as <hi>an Addition to Chriſt's Inſtitutions.</hi> But if by this Expreſſion he means the enjoyning and enacting an uncommanded thing, as if God himſelf had immediately Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded it; and ſo counterfeiting and ſtamping the Divine Authority, upon that which is no more but a humane Tradition, or Inſtitution (which to me ſeems the very utmoſt intent of that part of the Precept which he quotes <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 32.) He cannot but know that no manner of guilt can be faſtned on our Church upon this account: Becauſe ſhe plainly and fully di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhes between the <hi>unalterable</hi> Commands of God, and her own Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical inſtitutions, which ſhe acknowledges to be <hi>alterable,</hi> and not of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Obligation.</p>
            <p>Towards the end of that Paragraph o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my Addreſs which we are ſtill upon, I had deſired to know, <hi>ſince Cerem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>s might be uſed without Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition; how we could more effectually d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the uſe of them, than we already do?</hi> To which he returns me th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>more effectual way is to diſclaim all uſe of them:</hi> Which is juſt as if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaid, that the beſt way <hi>to uſe Ceremonies</hi> without Superſtition is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> at all; And if that be not a Contradiction, I know not what is. But here I muſt tell him that as there is no manner of Superſtition, either in preſcribing or practiſing a thing which God has le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> indifferent, as long as we retain and profeſs the true Opinion of its indifferency; ſo to diſclaim wholly the uſe of any thing, which in it ſelf is lawful, as if it were forbidden by God, when really it is not ſo; is in my apprehenſion a groſs piece of Superſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: And therefore to diſclaim all uſe of Ceremonies is not ſo effectual a way to avoid Superſtition, as our Author would have us believe; but rather the quite contrary: For <hi>to lay any Weight upon, and to be guided by, groundleſs imaginations of our own, in matters relating either to God's Providence or Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is</hi> what I take to be the proper and true notion of <hi>Superſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> And as this Practiſe of diſclaiming all our Ceremonies in the Worſhip of God would Evidently be Superſtition; ſo the Principle upon which our Author preſſes, it is, as plainly as can be, no leſs than the <hi>Addition of a Negative Precept to the Law of God.</hi> For he tells us <hi>that whatever i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not Commanded by God, and is required by Men, as a means of the Worſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p of God, is forbidden by God;</hi> Upon which he would have us lay all our Ceremonies aſide. But no ſuch Prohibition as this appears in the Law of God, either in expreſs words or by a fair and juſt conſequence, (as I have plainly ſhewn by examining all the plac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of Scriptur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> him). I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> this is an Addition of his own; And there one let him ſee to it how he can avoid or excuſe the breaking of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which he Quotes, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12. 32.</p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rd main propo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in my Addreſs, is a Corollary wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the two pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ding ones;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:37665:18"/> 
               <hi>viz. If in the Communion of our Church there be neither any thing wanting which is neceſſary to Salvation</hi> (which was my firſt propoſition) <hi>nor any thing pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in it which is ſinful</hi> (which was my ſecond Propoſition) then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>our Communion is at leaſt innocent,</hi> and not unlawful: In which ſequel if the Premiſes hold good (as I think I have juſtified them againſt all our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Objections) the concluſion cannot be denied or doubted of. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe mens Actions are generally regulated, not ſo much according to the <hi>Reallity</hi> of things, as according to their own <hi>Judgment and Apprehenſion of them;</hi> I proceeded to conſider whether it might be a juſt cauſe for men to refuſe communion with us upon either of theſe accounts; <hi>viz. That they judged our Communion unlawful;</hi> altho' <hi>really and in it ſelf it were not ſo;</hi> or elſe that they <hi>doubted whether it were lawful or not;</hi> and therefore thought it the beſt way not to joyn with us as long as this doubt remained unreſolved.</p>
            <p>As to the former of theſe; <hi>who judge our communion abſolutely unlawful;</hi> I in my Addreſs refer them to what I had before ſaid; And tell them that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they can ſhew wherein the Sin of our Communion lies; their <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> muſt needs be <hi>falſe and uncharitable:</hi> And as our Author deſires that what he has ſaid upon this Subject may be <hi>conſidered,</hi> ſo I entreat the Reader likewiſe to <hi>conſider</hi> the Anſwers which I have now returned to every materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al thing which he has urged.</p>
            <p>As to the other ſort, who do not abſolutely judge our Communion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful, but <hi>only doubt,</hi> or <hi>are not well aſſured</hi> concerning the lawfulneſs of it; I propoſe to them the common rule which is given in doubtful caſes; <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſhould <hi>chooſe that way which is moſt ſafe and free from the danger of Sin.</hi> But <hi>how,</hi> ſays our Author <hi>ſhall a Perſon who is not able to clear his doubts, about which is the moſt ſafe way, yet chooſe the moſt ſafe way?</hi> I anſwer that ſuch a Perſon indeed, while the doubt is equal on both ſides, has no certain rule to chooſe by. But if the doubt on the one ſide be very ſtrong, and founded upon the plain principles of Scripture or reaſon; and that on the other ſide, upon a ſtrict Examination, appears to be no more but a <hi>Scruple</hi> or groundleſs fear ariſing from fancy or prejudice, and not from any clear and rational Judgment of things; in ſuch a caſe as this, altho' ſome ſort of doubt may yet remain concerning the lawfulneſs of the Action; yet may it plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appear which is the ſafeſt way, and leſt liable to the danger of Sin. For tho' I allow with <hi>Cicer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> whom our Author quotes as agreeing with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Man ought not to do any thing, concerning the lawfulneſs of which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>doubt;</hi> yet ſtill I will venture to affirm with Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> De Couſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 6. That <hi>many ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rrples there are which, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> cannot be removed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the contrary, ought, by a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rce, to be laid aſide, and not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> And I preſume o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r Auth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, will allow <hi>this Doctor</hi> to be as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> as the <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to acquaint the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> I do not deſerve the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:37665:18"/>
            <p>In Order then to find out which is the ſafeſt way, for ſuch doubting Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to take, and to ſhew that the ſcruples, from whence ſuch doubtfulneſs ariſes in them, are groundleſs. I very briefly, yet I think plainly, urged theſe following things, <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>no man ought to deviate from a plain and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent law of God on account of ſuch Suggeſtions as he owns to be but obſcure and doubtful:</hi> That <hi>to promote the Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Church, and to give Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Commands of Lawful Authority, are very plainly and evidently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by God:</hi> That <hi>in this preſent caſe, the Suggeſtions, upon which ſuch a doubting Perſon refrains from our Communion, are ſuppoſed to be but doubtful and obſcure.</hi> (For if they were clear and plain, it would alter the Caſe; and the Perſon of whom we are ſpeaking would no longer remain in doubt; but be abſolutely determined in his Judgment) And laſtly, <hi>that a doubt in Point of Conſcience which, after a reaſonable time for enquiry, never comes to any poſitive Determination, is more probably the effect of fancy or prejudice than of any Sober and impartial Reaſoning; And therefore ought not to be put into the Ballanco againſt ſuch plain Commands of God; as do not admit of any doubt at all.</hi> Now he that has as little <hi>Reaſon and Divinity,</hi> as our Author will allow me to have, may yet ſee, that he gives a very illogical Anſwer to theſe things, which I have thus offered. For without the leſt offer made to confute my premiſes, or ſhew they are unconcluſive, he falls directly foul upon the concluſion it ſelf; and repeats the ſame Objection which I had before made; <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>to conform doubtingly either for Peace, or in Obedience to the Magiſtrate, is Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Conformity:</hi> For <hi>he that doubteth is damned, if he eat, and whatſoever is not of Faith, is Sin,</hi> p. 105. To which I Anſwer, that a doubt concerning the lawfulneſs of Obedience, to any humane Command is a very juſt reaſon for a man to <hi>ſuſpend acting,</hi> until ſuch time as he has made enquiry into the matter: But if after all he can find no ſolid and rational Foundation for this doubt; he ought to look upon it as no more but a meer <hi>Scruple,</hi> and to deal with it according to the direction which I have juſt now quoted out of Dr. <hi>Ames:</hi> For i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> we muſt forever forbear Acting, upon account of ſuch ſort of doubts as theſe; the conſequence will be almoſt perpetual perplexity of Conſcience, to all thoſe who are not able clearly and diſtinctly to Solve all the little Scruples, which either the Devil or their own weak fancies, may at any time raiſe in their minds; which would render Religion unto ſuch Perſons, as a yoke impoſſible to be born.</p>
            <p>And here by the way, I deſire the Reader to take Notice, how dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly our Author perverts my words, only by the omiſſion of one Syllable in his recital of them. In that part of my Addreſs now under Conſideration, I have theſe words; <hi>If a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter a reaſonable time for enquiry, be is not able to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine this doubt, ſo as poſitively to ſatisfie himſelf upon ſolid grounds, that ſuch Conformity is</hi> unlawful; <hi>what reaſon can be given, why ſuch a doubt ſhould be put
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:37665:19"/> in the Ballance; againſt thoſe plain Commands of God which I have mention'd.</hi> Now in the recital of theſe words of mine, our Author inſtead of the word <hi>unlawful,</hi> puts the word <hi>lawful,</hi> p. 105. So that whereas my Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in effect, runs thus, <hi>viz. Becauſe a Man is no way convin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d that ſuch a thing is</hi> unlawful, <hi>there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore be ought to do it, if lawful Authority commands it,</hi> (which I take to be very Reaſonable,) Our Author would inſinuate to the World, as if I had me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt that, <hi>becauſe a Man is not convinc'd that ſuch a thing is</hi> lawful; <hi>therefore he ought to do it if Authority requires it:</hi> which is altogether abſurd and void of Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quence.</p>
            <p>But <hi>why,</hi> ſay I, <hi>is it not as much a Sin doubtingly to refuſe Conformity, as doubtingly to conform?</hi> To this Queſtion, he returns me, pag. 106, back to S. <hi>Paul</hi> for an Anſwer; who ſays, that <hi>he that doubteth is Damned if he eat;</hi> But does not ſay, that <hi>he who doubteth is Damned, if he refuſe to eat.</hi> But I find that a <hi>little more Reaſon and Divinity,</hi> would do our Author no more hurt than it would me; which if he had, it <hi>would have taught him,</hi> that in the Caſe propoſed by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> the doubt could only be upon one ſide of the Queſtion, becauſe there was no Law, either of God or Man, which Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to eat the things there ſpoken of; and therefore there could be no ſuſpicion of Sin, in refuſing to eat them: For, <hi>where there is no Law, there is no Tranſgreſſion.</hi> But in our Caſe there are two plain Laws, <hi>viz. That of Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in the Church, and that of Obedience unto the higher Powers;</hi> both of them enacted by God, and both of them requiring our Conformity to the Eſtabliſhed Worſhip, except we can aſſign ſomething therein, which is unlawful: And therefore here the doubt muſt be as well on this ſide of the Queſtion as the other; And why a man's doubts in ſuch a Caſe as this, ſhould determine him to Diſobedience, and not rather to O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience; (the later being <hi>plainly</hi> and <hi>expreſsly</hi> required, and the former being only grounded upon ſome dark and obſcure ſuggeſtions) is what I believe all our Authors <hi>Reaſon and Divinity,</hi> will not be able plainly and clearly to account for.</p>
            <p>But our Author will not allow <hi>thoſe who ſo halt between two Opinions, as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to follow God nor</hi> Baal, to be <hi>Nonconformiſts, or of his Party any more than of ours!</hi> The plain Engliſh of which ſeems to be, that <hi>to be a Nonconformiſt, is to follow God;</hi> But, <hi>to be of the Eſtabliſhed Church is a following of</hi> Baal. And if ſuch little ſcruples and doubts as may ariſe, upon what he has above in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinuated concerning <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu, &amp;c.</hi> do keep a Man fixed in Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity, it ſhall be well approved of: But if the Peace and Unity of the Church, and Obedience to the Law of the Land, ſhall have ſo much influence upon him, as to put him! but in <hi>ſuſpenſe</hi> concerning what is beſt to be done; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with him, he halts between God and <hi>Baal;</hi> And ſince <hi>he gathereth not with</hi> our Author, he is to be rejected as one that <hi>ſcattereth.</hi> But I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:37665:19"/> to the preceding Paragraph, in which, as I ſaid, he endeavours to run down my Concluſion, without ſo much as offering to refute my Premiſſes.</p>
            <p>And here he goes on, and tells me, that <hi>a little more Reaſon and Divinity, would have taught me that Negative Precepts bind ad ſemper, But poſitive precepts bind only Semper.</hi> I Anſwer, that I have indeed met with this in my ſmall reading in <hi>Divinity;</hi> but how to apply it to his Purpoſe, my <hi>Reaſon</hi> does not inſtruct me. And therefore ſince he was ſo ſenſible of my defects herein, he ſhould have informed, and n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t amuſed me. All that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>urge is, that the <hi>poſitive precepts,</hi> of the Churches Unity, and Obedience to the Laws, may be allowed to oblige us ſo far, as not to Act contrary to them without a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al neceſſity: And that a <hi>Negative precept,</hi> of not acting with a doubting mind, may not be ſo far extended beyond its due intent and meaning, as that little and groundleſs ſcruples ſhould be allowed, to out-ballance the plain and evident commands of God: And how our Authors <hi>School Notions</hi> do any way contradict this reaſonable offer, I proteſt I cannot find out. He tells me, 2. That <hi>a Rule againſt which there is no Exception, will over-ballance that which is limited by Exceptions.</hi> But if the former of theſe Rules which concerns a doubting mind, preſſes with equal force upon both the Scales; and makes as much againſt <hi>refuſing Conformity,</hi> as againſt <hi>Conforming,</hi> (as I have ſhewn it does) then I hope the latter Rule, which enjoyns Peace Unity, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and Obedience to Authority, and inclines to one ſide only, ought in all Reaſon to <hi>turn the Ballance.</hi> But 3. he tells me, that <hi>if my Epiſcopal brethren in</hi> Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, <hi>ſhould doubt of the lawfulneſs of ſubmitting to Preſbytery, now by Law Eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed there; by my Rule they are bound to Conform for Peace, and in Obedience to Authority, and why don't I preach this to them.</hi> To which I anſwer that a bare doubt, which never comes to a poſitive determination on the one ſide or other, (and therefore, in my Opinion, muſt proceed from fancy or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice only, and not from ſound Reaſon) ought not, I think, to be put in the Ballance againſt the Commands of lawful Authority: But to apply this general Rule, to the Conſtitutions of any other Church, except our own, I conceive to be none of my buſineſs. But if our Author has a mind, to have my Doctrine Propagated in <hi>Scotland;</hi> he may if he pleaſes ſend my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs into that Kingdom. But, ſays he, by this Rule <hi>if a Man in</hi> France <hi>or</hi> Spain, <hi>ſhould be in doubt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ether Popery, or Proteſtantiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> were the ſafeſt, he ought to be a Papiſt in Obed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nce to Authority.</hi> I anſwer, that the conſequence will not hold. For altho' it may be a Mans duty to obey, ſuch Commands of Authority, <hi>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are in themſelves lawful,</hi> not withſtanding ſome doubts or ſcruples which he has to the contrary; yet will it not follow from hence, that therefore he is equally obliged to obey ſuch Commands, <hi>as are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves unlawful;</hi> which is what he would faſten upon me: But how far even in this Caſe, a man may be obliged to follow the dectates of a Conſcience;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:37665:20"/> which is but imperfectly informed is none of my buſineſs here to enquire.</p>
            <p>Our Author tells us, that <hi>we may not follow Peace or obey ſuperiors, except in Faith; And therefore to conform doubtingly is a Sin.</hi> From whence I may certainly, <hi>à Fortiori,</hi> infer, that therefore we ought not <hi>to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cak Peace,</hi> or <hi>diſobey Superiors,</hi> except in Faith; and therefore, <hi>doubtingly to refuſe Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, will be a greater Sin;</hi> which is what I offered in my Addreſs, He tells us alſo that <hi>our Obedience to Superiors, is limited by lawfulneſs, poſſibility, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedience, and edification.</hi> Now that no Authority can lay an obligation upon any Man, to do a thing, which is either <hi>unlawful</hi> or <hi>impoſſible,</hi> is very certain: But where the thing Commanded, is both lawful and poſſible; for a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to reſuſe Obedience, becauſe it is not <hi>Expedient;</hi> or does not tend to <hi>Edification;</hi> is what I cannot ſo readily approve of, except I have ſome bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Argument for it than our Author's bare Aſſertion. And I would fain be informed by him, who in this Caſe, is to be judge of the <hi>expediency</hi> and <hi>edification</hi> of the thing commanded? If the Superiors; then ſince our Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators have judged our Conſtitutions, to be expedient and edifying, no Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument can be drawn from hence, againſt our Conformity to them. But if every Subject muſt herein be a Judge for himſelf; ſince the Expediency and Edification of things, cannot always be brought under certain and fixed Rules, but are many times very variable in divers Caſes, and different cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; And ſince the Apprehenſions alſo of different Men, are herein very various, according to their divers Fancies, Prejudices or Inclinations; What is this but to ſet up, not only the <hi>Conſcience,</hi> but even the ſickle Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agination of every private Man to control Authority, whenſoever the Humour ſhall take him, or any crafty Man, who would gain him to his Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhall impoſe upon him? Which is much more eaſy to do, in relation to the <hi>Expediency</hi> or <hi>Edification</hi> of a thing, than the lawfulneſs or poſſibility of it.</p>
            <p>Having diſpatch'd the Objection againſt our Communion, which is drawn from the doubts and ſcruples, which ſome men have entertain'd, concerning the lawfulneſs of it; I proceed in the next place in my Addreſs, to propoſe and anſwer that which is taken from the pretence of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty:</hi> And becauſe our Author ſeems to have taken more than ordinary care to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex this part of the Diſpute; I muſt crave the Readers patience, while I take a little pains fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly to open and clear it.</p>
            <p>As God Almighty had by <hi>Moſes</hi> given a <hi>Written Law</hi> unto the Children of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> ſo, in proceſs of time, the Scribes and Phariſees had not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced divers <hi>Traditions</hi> of their own, (ſome of which might poſſibly in themſelves have been innocent, tho' unnec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſary) but alſo required the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of theſe Traditions, not only as immediate parts of the Law of God; but alſo, in ſome caſes, to be preferred even before the precepts of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:37665:20"/> the written Law, whenever they ſhould come in competition one with the other; of which we have a pretty full account in the former part of the <hi>7th</hi> Chapter of St. <hi>Mark</hi>'s Goſpel. Now when many of the Jews began to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Chriſtian Faith; ſome there were who either out of a ſecret deſign to obſtruct the progreſs of the Goſpel, or a profound veneration for that Inſtitution, under which they had been brought up; taught this Doctrine in the Chriſtian Church, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>Circumciſion</hi> and the <hi>Obſervation of the Law</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> were abſolutely <hi>neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> notwithſtanding that Chriſt was come into the World, as we are informed, <hi>Acts</hi> 15. 1. 24. And as they had generally received the above mention'd <hi>Traditions</hi> with an equal, and in ſome caſes a greater reſpect than what they had for the <hi>written Law;</hi> ſo did they no leſs endeavour to obtrude the one than the other upon all thoſe who had, or ſhould Embrace Chriſtianity. And notwithſtanding that the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Elders</hi> upon the firſt broaching of this Doctrine, endeavoured to ſuppreſs and put a ſtop to it, <hi>Act. 15. 6, &amp;c.</hi> yet, for all this, we find that it took root and prevailed, more or leſs, in divers of the Chriſtian Churches.</p>
            <p>To eaſe the Conſciences therefore of all the Faithful from ſuch an unne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and unſupportable burden, and alſo to free Chriſtianity from ſuch a clog as muſt needs very much retard the progreſs of it; the Apoſtles of Chriſt, wherever there was occaſion, took conſtant care to inform all who had received the Faith; of that freedom which Chriſt had given them from the Ordinances of the Moſaick Law, as well as from all other uncertain Traditions, which ſome men, without any other Authority but their own groundleſs fancies, would impoſe upon them; and alſo to exhort them to maintain, and by no means betray that liberty which was thus vouchſafed unto them: Of which I need not ſtand to produce any In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, becauſe the thing is not only confeſt on all hands, but alſo moſt notorious to all who do but read the Epiſtles of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and particularly thoſe to the <hi>Galatians</hi> and <hi>Coloſſians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus far then the Scripture does, undoubtedly, require every Chriſtian to aſſert and ſtand faſt in his liberty; <hi>viz. Not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it or own any thing as an eſſential part of Religion, and therefore neceſſary to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ion, which God has not directly required and preſcribed as ſuch.</hi> For which, the Reaſon I have given in my <hi>Addreſs,</hi> is unanſwerable; namely, that <hi>if way be given to ſuch ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rt of impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ſo many things, through pride or ignorance, may be introduced into Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, as to make it a yoke too heavy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be born.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things then I think there are, which, if fainly ſtated and cleared, muſt, one way or other, put an end to the difference between our Author and me, concerning this point: Namely, firſt, whether the obligation which lies upon us to maintain our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> ought to be extended
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:37665:21"/> any farther than thoſe bounds which I have now ſet toit? And if not, then ſecondly, whether this obligation (even as I have ſtated it) can, either by the letter of Scripture, or parity of Reaſon, be-juſtly ſo conſtrued as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain any man from yielding Conformity to any of the Conſtitutions of the Eſtabliſhed Church? upon which two things I deſire the Reader ſtill to have an eye, whilſt I am examining what our Author has ſaid, which may relate to either of them: For I cannot ſo well handle them each a-part, becauſe I am confined to follow that path in which he has thought fit to lead me.</p>
            <p>He tells me then, <hi>pag.</hi> 107. that I <hi>have not faithfully framed the Non-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts Objection;</hi> For their Notion, it ſeems, of Chriſtian Liberty, and the obligation to maintain it, is ſome what different from mine; and if <hi>things in their own nature indifferent</hi> are <hi>impoſed</hi> (tho not as eſſential parts of Religion, or neceſſary to Salvation) but only <hi>as parts or means of Worſhip, or Conditions of Communion in it;</hi> this, according to him, is an <hi>infringement</hi> of that Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian <hi>Liberty, in which we are bound to ſtand faſt.</hi> To which I anſwer, Firſt, That ſince the Worſhip of God is <hi>an eſſential part of Religion;</hi> to impoſe any thing <hi>as a part of Worſhip,</hi> would be to impoſe it as an <hi>eſſential part of Religion:</hi> For (as he has thought it neceſſary to inform me, p. 102.) <hi>quod eſt pars partis eſt pars totius.</hi> As therefore he has, thus far, ſaid no more than what I had ſaid before him; ſo have I already ſhewn that thoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things, which by our Liturgy are required in the ſervice of God, are not impoſed <hi>as parts of Worſhip;</hi> and therefore there ought on this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to be no Controverſie about them. Secondly, To ſubmit to ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things as are impoſed <hi>expreſsly not as parts of Worſhip,</hi> but only as the <hi>means,</hi> way or manner of performing it (provided that ſuch impoſing proceed from <hi>Lawful Authority)</hi> I have already ſhewn not to be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and have anſwered all our Author's pretences to the contrary: Nor can I upon his aſſertion believe that ſuch a ſubmiſſion for peace and unities ſake, is any way a giving up of our Chriſtian Liberty, until I ſee ſome good proof for it, either expreſsly contained in, or evidently conſequent from God's Words; of which I believe he would not have been ſo ſparing, if the Bible would have afforded him any Texts, upon which to have grounded an Argument. Or <hi>if our Liturgy be,</hi> on this account, <hi>an infringement of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty, not only all other Churches are guilty of the ſame, but even the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory</hi> it ſelf, <hi>which impoſes ſome things in themſelves indifferent, cannot be excuſed from it.</hi> Which paſſage of my Addreſs he has thought ſit to ſlip over, with a very lame and imperfect Anſwer. Thirdly, To impoſe any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different things <hi>as Conditions of Communion,</hi> if it were done either with an expreſs declaration, or any evident implication or ſuppoſition, that no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion could lawfully be kept up in, or held with, any Church whatſoever, without the uſe of thoſe things which were ſo impoſed; this indeed would
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:37665:21"/> be to impoſe ſuch things as <hi>eſſential and neceſſary parts of Worſhip and Religion;</hi> and conſequently, on the impoſers part, an unlawful attempt upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty. But as I have ſhewn that this is none of our Churches caſe; who expreſsly owns ſuch her Conſtitutions to be alterable as juſt cauſe ſhall require; and neither rejects the Communion, nor condemns the Practice of any other Church which differs from her in ſuch things as theſe: So if the matter were even thus it ſelf; yet if any private Chriſtian ſhould, for Peace and Unity, ſo far comply with the Church, as to ſubmit to what ſhe had required, and practiſe what ſhe had thus Preſcribed; but yet with an Expreſs Declaration and open Proteſtation, that he did this not out of any neceſſity, which was ſuppoſed to be in the things themſelves, which he ſtill aſſerted to be in their own Nature indifferent; but only for peace ſake, and, as far as in him lay, to prevent all Schiſms or Diviſions; I cannot ſee how ſuch a Man as this could be condemned, as therein guilty of any Sin, or any way a betrayer of his <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi> And if in this my Opinion, I am perhaps miſtaken, I ſhall be very glad to be better informed; provided it be done with <hi>Clear</hi> and <hi>Solid</hi> Arguments from plain Scripture and Reaſon, and not with ſuch <hi>perplexed</hi> and <hi>triſling</hi> Suggeſtions, as we have hitherto met with from our Author. But Fourthly, Since (as our Author grants, p. 103) <hi>without Circumſtances, Worſhip cannot be performed, and all outward Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Worſhip are not preſcribed by God.</hi> It muſt follow, either that ſome outward Circumſtances of Worſhip may be determined and appointed by Man, or elſe the Worſhip of God cannot poſſibly be performed. Suppoſe then that the Church appoints and determines ſome indifferent things, as Circumſtances in Gods Worſhip; and requires them to be obſerved by all her Members; And yet that ſome are ſo Obſtinate and Refractory, as that they will not ſubmit to her Authority in theſe things: What is to be done in ſuch a Caſe as this? muſt every particular M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n be left to his liberty, to introduce what Circumſtances he pleaſes into the Worſhip of God, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his own Fancy or Inclination? This would be the direct way to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found that <hi>Order,</hi> and deſtroy that <hi>Decency,</hi> for which the Apoſtle particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly provides, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 40, as I have ſaid in my Addreſs; And to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the <hi>Directory</hi> as well as the <hi>Liturgy.</hi> Or muſt the Church from time to time, alter and new modell her Conſtitutions, concerning the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of God, Worſhip until matters are ſo ſetled, as that every one may be pleaſed and fully ſatisfied? This I confeſs were a moſt excellent way, if the thing were at all practicable or poſſible to be performed: But when it is conſidered that in ſuch matters as relate to Order and Decency only, we have not always a fixed and certain Rule, as to particulars; but Men have different Opinions of ſuch things, according to the difference of their Cuſtoms, Tempers, and Educations; I believe it will be found a very hard,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:37665:22"/> and perhaps an impoſſible thing, ſo to frame all the Circumſtances of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Worſhip, as that all ſorts of Men, how different ſoever in their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or Education, ſhall be well pleaſed and ſatisfied with them. And if this be not to be done; then, it may be, if any Church ſhould go about to make alterations in ſuch things, to pleaſe and gratifie ſome People; they might hereby diſpleaſe and diſguſt many others; and ſo in the end do more hurt than good by ſuch Alterations. What then remains? but that every Church in ſuch things as theſe muſt act according to the beſt of her prudence; And if men will ſtill be refractory and not ſubmit to ſuch Conſtitutions as lawful Authority enjoins, and are no way contrary to the Law or Word of God; I would gladly know what other courſe is at laſt to be taken with them, but to exclude them from the Communion of the Society, who thus obſtinately refuſe to conform to the Rules and Orders of it? And if our Author judges this to be an <hi>infringement of Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> I deſire he would not only ſay it, but alſo clearly and ſolidly prove it.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Chriſt has freed us from all parts and parcels of Worſhip which are not of his own Inſtitution!</hi> He has ſo: But what is this to thoſe Ceremonies which I have plainly proved to be no <hi>parts</hi> (or <hi>parcels)</hi> but only <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of Worſhip? <hi>He has freed us alſo from all Conditions of Communion but thoſe of his own Preſcribing!</hi> very right: But then we muſt remember that one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of Communion which Chriſt preſcribes unto us, is to <hi>obey them that have the rule over us, and ſubmit our ſelves,</hi> Heb. 13. 17. To <hi>be ſubject to the higher powers,</hi> Rom. 13. 1. And to <hi>ſubmit our ſelves to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. And whoſoever <hi>obſtinately refuſes</hi> to perform this condition, is juſtly to be excluded from the Communion of the Church, as a diſobeyer of Chriſt's Commands. Now the Queſtion is, Wherein and in what ſort of things is this obedience and ſubjection to be ſhewn? Not in things immediately or directly commanded by the Law of God: For in ſuch things as thoſe our obedience is paid to God alone, and not to our Earthly Superiours; And the obligation is the ſame, if my <hi>Inferiour</hi> informs me that ſuch is the Will of God, as if my Superiour lays his commands therein up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me. Nor yet in ſuch things as are contrary to God's Law: For if our Superiours ſhould command any thing of that nature, <hi>we ought to obey God ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than man, Acts</hi> 5. 29. It remains then, that <hi>things in their own nature in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different, when required by lawful Authority, are the proper and adequate matter wherein our obedience to our Superiours, whether Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, is to be ſhewn.</hi> And as all Superiours ought to exerciſe their power of commanding with Prudence and Charity, as they ſhall anſwer for the ſame before the Throne of God; ſo are all inferiours moſt evidently obliged in Conſcience to be conformable and obedient to ſuch commands, when the matter there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:37665:22"/> is lawful in it ſelf: nor is ſuch conformity any way inconſiſtent with our <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſays he, <hi>hath allowed us the uſe of indifferent things indifferently, as Chriſtian Prudence and Charity ſhall determine!</hi> I grant it. But then I would know why the <hi>uſe</hi> of ſuch things may not, in ſome caſes, as well be <hi>determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Chriſtian Prudence and Charity of the Church</hi> for the whole Society, as in other caſes by thoſe of every private man for himſelf? Except it be that ſome men have a very ſtrong inclination to be guided by their own fancies, rather than by the will of their Superiors. But this, ſays he, would be <hi>ſo to determine our practice, as to deſtroy its indifferency!</hi> I Anſwer, that this indeed would make it the duty of every private man to conform his practice in ſuch indifferent things, to the Law that is over him, as long as that Law re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in force (in which I ſee not the leaſt inconvenience or abſurdity): but would not ſo far deſtroy the indifferency either of the thing, or our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; but that, upon the repeal of that Law which bound us, we ſhould be as much at liberty as ever we were. But our Author tells us, that <hi>the main violation of Chriſtian Liberty lies in a fixt, ſtated and perpetual compulſion, to do what God hath permitted us to omit; or a prohibition to do what he hath made law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for us.</hi> I Anſwer; if, 1. The ſubject matter of this <hi>Compulſion</hi> or <hi>Prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition</hi> be in its own nature lawful or indifferent; If, 2. The <hi>Compulſion</hi> or <hi>Prohibition</hi> proceed from lawful Authority; And if, 3. It be by that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſufficiently declared, that this ſame <hi>Compulſion</hi> or <hi>Prohibition</hi> is not to be eſteemed as anexpreſs or immediate part of Gods Law; but only as a humane conſtitution, to which, while it remains in force (and no longer) we are in Conſcience obliged to give obedience, on account of the general Commands of God, which require us to be ſubject to our lawful Governours: Such a <hi>Compulſion</hi> or <hi>Prohibition</hi> as this, is no manner of <hi>violation of Chriſtian Liberty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But he will prove that it is, and that by the Authority of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> For <hi>thus,</hi> ſays he, <hi>the Apoſtle teacheth,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 12. <hi>All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any perſon or thing in matters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</hi> But, I ſay, the Apoſtle does not thus teach: And it is not only a moſt diſingenuous, but even an impious preſumption in this bold man thus to falſifie the Text of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>to add unto the Word of God,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his deſign therein may be. The words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the place quoted, are neither more nor leſs than theſe, <hi>All things are lawful unto me, but all things are not expedient: All things are lawful for me, but I will not be brought under the power of any.</hi> Where it is evident from the following verſe, that he ſpeaks only concerning the eating or forbearing of ſuch <hi>Meats</hi> as ſome indeed ſcrupled out of weakneſs; but which were not <hi>commanded</hi> or <hi>enjoined</hi> by any Law or Conſtitution either of God or Man. And our Author could
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:37665:23"/> not but ſee that it was impoſſible ſo far to extend St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s own words, as to bring them in the leaſt to countenance Diſobedience to lawful Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; and therefore that he muſt either add to them, or elſe not be able to produce ſo much as one Text of Scripture to prove that which with ſo much aſſurance he had aſſerted. But if he has a power given him to make Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture where he has it not ready to ſerve his purpoſe, I muſt confeſs it will be hard to diſpute with him. Nor can he here pretend that he ſets down the laſt words of the above mentioned quotation, not as a part of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Text, but only as his own Paraphraſe upon it: For (beſides that in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles own words, there is no manner of foundation for the inſerting of the word <hi>perſon)</hi> the whole Sentence, as I have above recited it, is all a-like printed in the Italick Character, and all of it equally referred to thoſe foregoing words <hi>[thus the Apoſtle teacheth]:</hi> which I think moſt plainly ſhews that it was our Author's deſign, that the whole Sentence ſhould paſs upon his unwary Readers, as if it were every Syllable taken out of the place from whence he has quoted it.</p>
            <p>But I ought not thus <hi>to bind up my ſelf from opportunity of uſing my Chriſtian Liberty for the Spiritual good of another!</hi> I Anſwer that, where a humane Law is made concerning any thing which otherwiſe were indifferent; Obedience <hi>ordinarily</hi> and <hi>generally</hi> ought to be given to that Law; Nor ought any man to ſwerve from it to gratifie the humour of ſuch as only reſolve to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe and obſtinate. But where a caſe ariſes to which the intention of the law-makers either did not or ought not to have extended, and where by acting otherwiſe than the Law preſcribes, ſome great good may be done, or evil avoided or remedied; If all even ſeeming <hi>contempt of Authority</hi> be meekly and prudently avoided, and juſt occaſion of ſcandal carefully prevented and obviated; I, for my part, ſhould no way condemn that man, who upon ſuch an emergency, in ſuch a manner, and with ſuch caution as this, ſhould act otherwiſe than the letter of the humane Law ſhould preſcribe. In which opinion the generality of Learned Caſuiſts that I have happened to look into, do unanimouſly concur with me. And therefore what preſently follows, is ſpoken without any other ground but his own fancy, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>by ſuch impoſing and determining in matters indiffirent, more is attributed to the poſitive precepts of Men, than to the moral Laws of God.</hi> For I challenge our Author to produce me <hi>but one man</hi> of any repute of the Eſtabliſhed Church, who ever maintained that <hi>obedience</hi> to our Eccleſiaſtical, or to any humane Laws, may not <hi>pro hic &amp; nunc be ſuſpended to give way to a greater good,</hi> as well as <hi>obedience to the poſitive moral Laws of God.</hi> And as for <hi>making that a ſin which God has made lawful</hi> by not forbidding it, which is another of his ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, I have already anſwered it: And it is enough to ſay, that God has not made it lawful to diſobey lawful Authority in ſuch things as are indifferent.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:37665:23"/>
            <p>From what I have hitherto been diſcourſing upon this ſubject, I think it may clearly be gathered, that notwithſtanding all that our Author has ſaid to the contrary, the obligation of maintaining our Chriſtian Liberty is no farther to be extended than as I had ſet the bounds and limits of it. But what follows in the next Paragraph, is deſigned to ſhew, that allowing my notion of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty</hi> to be juſt and good, yet ſtill our Ceremonies are <hi>deſtructive</hi> of it, becauſe they <hi>are made eſſential parts of Religion, and neceſſary to Salvation;</hi> which if he can but prove as clearly as he has confidently affirmed it, then indeed, and not otherwiſe, he might have reaſon to ſay that <hi>my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is not ſufficient to the Objection, even as I my ſelf had framed it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here I muſt deſire the Reader to take notice what a poor and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuous piece of Sophiſtry our Author endeavours to put upon the world. To convince the <hi>Non-Conformists</hi> that our Ceremonies were no infringement of Chriſtian Liberty, I gave them to underſtand, in my Addreſs, that our Church did not impoſe them <hi>as eſſential parts of Religion, and neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation:</hi> In oppoſition to which, he undertakes to prove that they <hi>are by us made eſſential parts of Religion, and neceſſary to Salvation;</hi> and therefore <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of Chriſtian Liberty:</hi> But when he comes to produce his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he cunningly conceals the main and fundamental part of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion which he was to prove; and as for the other part of it, which was but an appendage to, or ſuperſtructure upon the former, he perverts and plainly alters the ſenſe and meaning of it.</p>
            <p>The fundamental part of the concluſion which he undertakes to prove, is, that <hi>our Ceremonies are by us made eſſential parts of Religion.</hi> But in order to make this good, he does not ſo much as offer the leaſt word or ſyllable. The other part is, that <hi>we make them neceſſary to Salvation:</hi> which indeed he attempts to prove; but in a clear different ſenſe from that in which I denied it. My meaning was plainly this, that our Church did not pretend that her Ceremonies <hi>were immediately derived from the eſſence of Religion,</hi> or upon that account neceſſary to be obſerved; which I grant would be an encroachment upon Chriſtian Liberty: But all that his, Arguments can pretend to prove, is, that our Ceremonies, being impoſed by the Laws of the Church, the uſe of them is eſteemed neceſſary to Salvation; not as being eſſential parts of Religion, or ſo reputed by us, but only as they are the matter wherein we ought to ſhew our conformity and obedience to the commands of lawful Authority. In Anſwer therefore to all his Arguments at once, I ſhall only tell him, that obedience to the lawful commands of lawful Authority, is one of thoſe Duties which God has made neceſſary to Salvation: And as far as any Ceremony is the matter of ſuch obedience, ſo far it is, by conſequence, in its proper degree, alſo neceſſary, altho' it be no eſſential part of Religion: Nor is there any thing
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:37665:24"/> herein which is any way deſtructiue of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi> But that which he ſhould have proved, was, that we eſteem our Ceremonies to be neceſſary to Salvation, even antecedently to the commands of the Church and the Law.</p>
            <p>That therefore our Author's Arguments, which he here urges, are all of them wide from the point in Controverſie, is as evident as may be: But becauſe in ſome of them he has a ſly deſign, not ſo much to prove what he had juſt before undertaken, as to render the Eſtabliſhed Church as black and odious as may be in the eyes of his Party; It will be neceſſary before I proceed, to wipe off that dirt which here he rakes together to throw at her.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place then, I muſt tell him, that what I have hitherto read of his Book, has not begot in me ſuch an opinion of his veracity, as, upon his bare word, to make me give credit to what he ſuppoſes, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>the bare omiſſion of Ceremonies, tho' out of tenderneſs of Conſcience, is by us judged Schiſm, Sedition, and Rebellion; and made worthy of Fining, Impriſonment, and Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication:</hi> Nor have I any reaſon to think his good nature towards us to be ſo abundant, as that he would have omitted to quote ſome paſſages of our Laws or Canons, if any ſuch there had been, to make good this charge to the utmoſt, which he thus aggravates againſt us. That Conſciences which are <hi>truly tender,</hi> ought ever to be uſed with the greateſt gentleneſs, is the unanimous opinion of all ſober and good men that ever I remember to have met with, either of our own or any other of the Reformed Churches: And altho' in the Letter of Humane Laws, an exception or diſpenſation for tender Conſciences is no way proper to be expreſsly inſerted; becauſe every man being able to make this pretence, and none but God, who knows the hearts of men, being able to confute it, where it is falſely, but craftily made; this would be the way wholly to enervate the ſanction and force of all ſuch Laws, and ſo to leave it at every mans pleaſure, whether he would obſerve them or not: yet in the execution of them (at leaſt of all ſuch as concern Religion and the Worſhip of God), I freely grant, that a due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard ought to be had to the invincible miſtakes of all ſuch as appear to be well-meaning men; becauſe it ought ever to be preſumed, that the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law-makers was not, or ought not to have been, that ſuch ſort of men as they ſhould be ſeverely dealt with. And if any particular men have ever preſt the Execution of our Eccleſiaſtical Laws beyond this; Let them anſwer for themſelves; for I am ſure I ſhall never appear in their defence. But where there are moſt ſtrong preſumptions that it is not real tenderneſs of Conſcience, but ſome other principle, which prompts a man not only himſelf to refuſe obedience to lawful Authority, but alſo to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade as many as he can to join with him therein; Where a man can with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out remorſe or ſcuple break ſome of the moſt known Laws of God; can
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:37665:24"/> confidently vent ſuch ſlanders and calumnies, as are not only contrary to charity, but alſo to truth it ſelf; and can pervert and miſquote, not only the Writings of a Man, but even the Word of God; and yet all this while ſhall refuſe to obey ſuch commands of Authority, as he cannot ſhew to be either expreſsly or by good conſequence contrary to any Law or Command of God; (which I have plainly ſhewn to be our Authors caſe). If ſuch a Man as this ſhall yet plead the <hi>tenderneſs of his Conſcience,</hi> for refuſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Laws of the Land, (which yet it ſeems is <hi>tough</hi> enough to diſpenſe with the violation of the above mentioned Laws of God) I would gladly know whether ſuch a plea, and in ſuch a caſe, is to be admitted: And if the penalty of the Law be not put in execution againſt a man who plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appears to be of this temper, I think he has more reaſon to thank the mildneſs of the Government, than to attribute it to any juſtice which he may pretend to be on his ſide, or favour that ought to be extended to him, on account of the tenderneſs of his Conſcience. But let a mans Conſciences be diſpoſed as it will; <hi>the bare omiſſion of Ceremonies</hi> is not by any of our Laws ſo ſeverely cenſured as our Author pretends; but was ſo wife as not to produce his proofs; nor is any man thereby condemned of <hi>Schiſm,</hi> except he makes or keeps up a ſeparation in the Church; nor of <hi>Sedition</hi> or <hi>Rebellion,</hi> except he helps to maintain a faction, or takes up arms againſt the Civil State; nor, laſtly, made ſubject to <hi>Fining, Impriſonment</hi> or <hi>Excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> except it be for <hi>publick Oppoſition to the Eſtabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhed Laws.</hi> And if our Author had not conſulted more with paſſion or ill nature, than with ſober reaſon or charity, he would never have ſo ſtrained things beyond their due pitch, as he has moſt evidently done in the above mentioned ſuggeſtion, which he brings in charge againſt us.</p>
            <p>Nor, Secondly, do I any where find it to be the Judgment of our Church, that every one who comes under the ſentence of Excommunication, muſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily be ſuppoſed to <hi>be delivered to Satan;</hi> which is another of his good natured inſinuations. That thoſe Perſons, who, by publick diſobedience and oppoſition to the lawful commands of lawful Authority, do <hi>cauſe diviſions and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ffences</hi> in the Church, ſhould be <hi>avoided,</hi> and excluded from her viſible Communion, is no more than what I think to be ſufficiently warranted by the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 16. 17. But becauſe it is poſſible, and ſometimes probable enough, that many men are thus miſſed, not ſo much by wilfulneſs or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinacy, as by ſome great miſtakes or ſtrong prejudices which they have entertained, or, it may be, by a real <hi>zeal of God, but not according to knowledge,</hi> we are ſo far from concluding any of them to be abſolutely given into the poſſeſſion of the Devil, that, on the contrary, we charitably hope that the generality of them will <hi>obtain mercy</hi> at the hand of God; not do we at all doubt it, where the diſobedience to Authority pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eds not from perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but ignorance of their Duty in this particular.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:37665:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:37665:25"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:37665:26"/>
            <p>Thirdly, Whereas he would have the world believe that <hi>the omiſſion</hi> of Ceremonies, <hi>makes a Miniſter more liable to deprivation than Whoredom, Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſs,</hi> &amp;c. If he means, that it is commonly more eaſie to convict ſuch an one of Nonconformity, which muſt be open and notorious, than of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morality, which may be kept ſo ſecret as, in many caſes, ſcarcely to admit of legal proof; I deſire to know how is this to be helpt, or the Church to be blamed for it? Or, if he means, that immorality in Miniſters has not been ſo ſtrictly proſecuted and puniſhed as Nonconformity: Beſides that he offers no manner of proof even of this; the utmoſt it could amount to, if true, would be to faſten a juſt blame, not upon the Laws of the Church, but upon thoſe Perſons who ſhould have put them in execution; wherein I will join with him, with all my heart, if he can but furniſh me with ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proof of the matter of fact. But if he means that, by our Eccleſiaſtical Laws, a Miniſter, who is <hi>convicted</hi> of ſuch immorality as he mentions, is not as liable to deprivation as he that is found guilty of Nonconformity, (which I think is the only meaning of his words, that can be any way to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe). I challenge the abominable falſehood of this aſſertion, and demand the proof of it from him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Whereas he ſuggeſts that <hi>the refuſers of Conformity,</hi> are <hi>judged worſe than Idolatrous Papiſts:</hi> This is an imputation ſo notoriouſly unjuſt and immodeſt, that none but a man of ſuch a <hi>tender Conſcience,</hi> as our Author would ever lay it to our charge. But 'tis no matter for that, his party will probably believe that he would never affirm a thing ſo extraordinary if it were not ſo; And if he does but calumniate ſtoutly, ſomething perhaps may ſtick. But methinks this man, who ſo ſolemnly in his Preface, appeals <hi>to the Judge that ſtandeth at the door,</hi> ſhould remember the account, which one day he muſt give of his <hi>words</hi> as well as <hi>actions,</hi> unto that ſame Judge.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, Whereas he accuſes us, that we eſteem our Ceremonies to <hi>be more neceſſary than the Peace and Unity of the Church.</hi> I Anſwer, that if any man were once <hi>convinced</hi> that the abolition of any Ceremonies, which law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully may be laid aſide, would generally conduce to the Unity and Peace of the Church; and that without doing any other hurt, which might over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ballance this good; and if, in this caſe, he ſhould refuſe to have theſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies aboliſhed; it might indeed juſtly be ſaid of him, that he preferred them before <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Unity.</hi> But where it no way appears that men are thus convinced: But on the contrary, that there is much reaſon to fear that the prohibition or diſuſe of ſuch Ceremonies, would not only give a very plauſible advantage to the Churches enemies, and ſcandalize a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of her own weak Members; but alſo encourage thoſe that cauſeleſly diſſent from her to inſult and triumph, and to demand other things, which are yet more unreaſonable. Where men, I ſay, are under theſe or ſuch
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:37665:26"/> like apprehenſions (as many ſober and prudent men of our Church are); altho' a man ſhould be of opinion that they were miſtaken, yet could he not, with truth or charity, affirm, that they preferred their Ceremonies, or thought them <hi>more neceſſary than the Peace and Unity of the Church.</hi> For in this caſe, bare Ceremonies are not put into the Scale againſt Peace and Unity, as our Author would inſinuate: But all the evil conſequences, which would attend the abolition of our Ceremonies, are ballanced againſt the uncertain ſatisfaction which might be given to ſome miſtaken men, whoſe principles, if they are followed, muſt continually lead them into new ſcruples and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, againſt all humane eſtabliſhments, in matters of Religion and the Worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>In the concluſion of this point of Chriſtian Liberty, I had ſaid in my <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs,</hi> that <hi>if our Liturgy were an inſringement of Chriſtian Liberry, not only all other Churches were guilty of the ſame; but even the Directory, which impoſes ſome things which in themſelves are indifferent, cannot be excuſed from it.</hi> To which, all the Anſwer that our Author gives, is, <hi>p.</hi> 109. to <hi>deny, and to demand proof from all who aſſert, that the Directory requireth any Ceremonies of myſtical ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation; or impoſeth any indifferent thing, ſave ſuch Circumſtances as nature and reaſon direct.</hi> But is not this meer ſhuffling, thus to take no notice of the thing which I had aſſerted, and to require me to prove that which I had never affirm'd, or ſo much as inſinuated? I had no occaſion to ſpeak of any ſuch thing as <hi>myſtical Ceremonies</hi> or <hi>improper Circumſtances</hi> to be preſcribed by the <hi>Directory:</hi> Nor therefore ſhould he have amuſed the Reader with the mention of them. The whole force of my Argument lay plainly in this alone, that if it be a violation of Chriſtian Liberty, for order and decency's ſake, to ſettle and determine any thing, in the manner or circumſtances of God's Worſhip, which God by his own immediate Law had not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined. From hence it would follow not only that all other Churches, but even the Directory it ſelf, which does determine ſome things which God had left indifferent, muſt be guilty of the violation of Chriſtian Liberty: To which, he does not think ſit to return any manner of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            <p>However, that our Author may not complain that I accuſe the Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory, as equally culpable with our Liturgy in the violation of Chriſtian Liberty, without giving any inſtances to make good what I ſay; It will not be amiſs here, to give an Example or two of ſuch things as I hint at for the Readers better ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A ſixt ſtated and perp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tual compulſion to do what God has permitted us to omit, or a prohibition to do what he has made lawful ſor us,</hi> is, according to our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, <hi>the main violation of Chriſtian liberty,</hi> p. 107. Now as it was lawful for the People of the Jews, to <hi>Worſhip towards Gods Holy Temple,</hi> where they
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:37665:27"/> dayly Sacrifice was offered, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 6. 26. <hi>Pſ.</hi> 5. 7. and 138. 2. And for <hi>Daniel</hi> to Worſhip <hi>towards Jeruſalem, Dan.</hi> 6. 10. As being the place where their ſolemn Devotions wereto be paid, whenever they could there be perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly preſent. By a fair parity of reaſon it is undoubtedly Lawful, for a Chriſtian to Worſhip God towards the reading desk, from whence the Prayers of the Congregation are offer'd up, and the Word of God read un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the People by the Miniſter; or towards the Pulpit, from whence the Word of God is opened and explained for our Uſe and Inſtruction; or to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Communion Table, where we often receive the Holy Symbols of the Body and Blood of Chriſt, which are the means appointed by him, whereby we are to Communicate in the Merits of his Paſſion. Nor is there any Law of God which, either in Words or by good Conſequence, in the leaſt forbids us to expreſs this Worſhip, by the bowing our Bodies. But the Directory, p. 10, does poſitively prohibit <hi>Adoration</hi> (that is Worſhip) <hi>or bowing ones ſelf towards one place or other:</hi> which is not only to <hi>forbid what God has made lawful;</hi> But alſo ſeems to require that which is in it ſelf Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. For in all Acts of Adoration, as long as we have Bodies, we muſt of neceſſity turn our ſelves <hi>towards ſome place or other;</hi> And I deſire our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, if he can, to ſhew me ſuch a prohibition in any part of our Liturgy. Again <hi>God has</hi> undoubtedly <hi>permitted us to omit</hi> the poſture of ſitting at the Reception of the Holy Communion; becauſe it neither appears that this was the very poſture, in which Chriſt and his Apoſtles received it; nor if it were, is there any Command that we ſhould imitate them in that Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, any more than in the time or place wherein they performed that Office; which was <hi>after Supper</hi> and in <hi>an Upper Room:</hi> But, by the Directo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Men are as much compelled to ſit, as by the liturgy to kneel, at the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Communion; The words of the former p. 51, that <hi>the Table</hi> is to be <hi>ſo conveniently plated, that the Communicants may orderly ſit about it,</hi> being alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as directive, as the Rubrick of the Latter; that <hi>the Miniſter</hi> ſhall deliver the Communion in both kinds to the People, <hi>all meekly kneeling;</hi> And the words of <hi>the Ordinance of Parliament, for the Eſtabliſhing and putting in Execution the Directory, viz.</hi> That the Directory <hi>ſhall be uſed, purſued, and Obſerved in all Exerciſes of the Publick Worſhip of God, in every Congregation,</hi> &amp;c. Being tho' Illegal, yet as injunctive as any Clauſe in either of the Acts of Uniformity, for the Uſing of the Liturgy; And laſtly, the poſture of ſitting (if I am rightly informed) having been as ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctly obſerved and kept to by the Nonconformiſts, in the receiving of the Holy Communion, as that of kneeling by thoſe of the Eſtabliſhed Church: And therefore the Directory, according to our Author, muſt be as much an infringement of Chriſtian Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, in this alſo, as our Liturgy.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:37665:27"/>
            <p>Having done with the Objection which was drawn from the pretence of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> In the next place I propoſed that which is raiſed from the pretended <hi>numerouſneſs</hi> and <hi>burthen</hi> of our Ceremonies; to which I Anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that <hi>the utmoſt that this could amount to,</hi> if it were true, (as I do not conceive that it is) <hi>would be only an inconvenience, and not a ſin.</hi> To which he Replies, <hi>p.</hi> 109, that <hi>God's word tells us, that to do what is not convenient is ſinful,</hi> Rom. 1. 28. Epheſ. 5. 4. But is not this ſtill meer triſling and playing with the ambiguity of a word, which I plainly take in one ſenſe, and he wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully miſtakes in another? For whereas a thing may be ſaid to be <hi>inconvenient,</hi> either firſt becauſe it is <hi>troubleſome;</hi> or ſecondly, becauſe it is <hi>unlawful:</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be more manifeſt, than that here I take the word <hi>inconvenient</hi> in the former ſenſe only, and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in the places he aſſigns, only in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. If our Ceremonies were too numerous and burthenſom (as I cannot ſee why they ſhould be ſo thought) yet this would only render them <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome,</hi> and upon that account <hi>inconvenient,</hi> but not unlawful: Whereas it is plainly the <hi>unlawfulneſs</hi> and not the troubleſomneſs of <hi>unrighteouſneſs, fornication, wickedneſs, covetouſneſs,</hi> &amp;c. and of <hi>filthineſs,</hi> and <hi>fooliſh talking</hi> and <hi>jeſting,</hi> which makes the Apoſtle in the above mentioned places, to call them by the name of <hi>inconvenient.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, ſays he, <hi>Was not this the ſin of the Phariſees,</hi> Mat. 23, 4. that they <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened</hi> mens <hi>Conſciences with their own inventions?</hi> To which I Anſwer, that the ſin of the Phariſees in that place muſt needs be one or both of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> either, firſt, the impoſing of humane Traditions, <hi>as a part of God's Law,</hi> of which I have already ſpoken, under the Objection about Chriſtian Liberty; or, ſecondly, the requiring a much more ſtrict and exact obedience to God's Law from other People, than what they themſelves performed (as appears from the two proceding verſes) which was a piece of moſt groſs Hypocriſie. But what relation this has to Rites and Ceremonies, appointed by Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for order and decency in the Worſhip of God, our Author muſt inform me, for of my ſelf I am not able to find it out.</p>
            <p>In my Addreſs I had taken notice, that <hi>tho' St.</hi> Auſtin <hi>complained of the number and burthen of Ceremonies in his time, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> never find that he looked upon that as any cauſe for ſeparating from the Eſtabliſhed Church:</hi> Upon which he thinks he has caught me ſeveral ways: And firſt he demands, <hi>why the Diſſenters may not now complain</hi> as well as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did in his time? To which I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, becauſe they have not the ſame reaſon; the number of Ceremonies, which were brought into the Church in his days, being much greater and more perplexing than what is now in uſe amongſt us. But yet if they now made their complaint, as he did, without breaking the Unity of the Church, or cauſing any Schiſm in it; altho' I ſhould think that there were no reaſon for their ſo complaining; yet ſhould I not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erein acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe them as guilty of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:37665:28"/> any ſin. But our Author tells us, that if St. <hi>Auſtin had lived in ſome places of the world, and complained of ſuch a lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>then, there is a Canon called the tenth, by which he had been, Ipſo fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>, ſhut out of the Church.</hi> To which I Anſwer, that neither are the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ipſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cio</hi> (upon which he lays ſuch weight) in the <hi>Tenth Canon</hi> of the Church of <hi>England;</hi> nor is the Excommunication there threatned, but upon a ſuppoſition that ſuch a complaint is made and <hi>publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> for the abetting and juſtifying of ſuch as make a Schiſm in the Church, by <hi>taking to themſelv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s the name of another Church, not Eſtabliſhed by Law:</hi> which farther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hews how diſingenuous a man this is in quotations. In the next place, he demands <hi>how do I know that St.</hi> Auſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in <hi>did not ſeparate?</hi> But was ever ſuch a Queſtion askt? Or is there the leaſt intimation either in his own or any other of the Books of that Age, that ever he did ſeparate? And if ſuch a man as he had ſeparated, is it to be imagined that great notice would not have been taken of it? Or laſtly, do I pretend to <hi>know poſitively</hi> that he did not ſeparate, or to ſay any more, but that <hi>we never find</hi> that he did? But our Author has a <hi>dilemma,</hi> to prove St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> either to have ſeparated or ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: For <hi>if he refuſed to uſe</hi> thoſe ſame Ceremonies, of which he complained, then <hi>he ſeparated as well as the preſent Non-conſormists:</hi> but <hi>if he uſed them after his complaint of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng burthenſome and too numerous, it would be hard to excuſe him from ſin.</hi> To this I Anſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er, firſt, that many Ceremonies in St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s days, being probably introduced by meer cuſtom, without any Law or Canon to eſtabliſh and confirm them; it was certainly lawful for him, in his own Church and Dioceſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the uſe of ſuch Ceremonies as theſe, as in prudence he might think ſit; becauſe in ſtrictneſs there lay no obligation upon him at all to make uſe of them. But, ſecondly, if he had renounced and abſolutely refuſed to communicate with any Chriſtian Church whatſoever, againſt which he had no other Objection, but only that they required the uſe of ſome Ceremonies in the Worſhip of God which God had not commanded, nor yet had any way forbidden; altho' theſe Ceremonies might have been too numerous; and upon that account trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome; yet i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he had no other j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> plea to bring againſt them, I cannot ſee how this alone could have juſtified him in breaking the Unity of the Church, which every Chriſtian is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nd, as far as in him lyes, to preſerve: But that ever he did any thing like this, does not in the leaſt appear. But, Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if St. <hi>Auſlin,</hi> for the ſake of Peace and Unity, was content to ſubmit to the uſe of ſo many Ceremonies as, in his opinion, were too numerous, and therefore burthenſome; I deſire our Author to inform m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, by what Law of God he can on this account be taxed, or with any reaſon ſo much as ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of ſin: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> tho' it is not lawful to <hi>do evil, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> may come,</hi> Rom. 3. 8. Yet that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uld b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay unlawful, to do a thing which is not evil, but only troubleſome and uneaſy; when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> a man has in doing it is really
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:37665:28"/> good; is what no man, I think, of common ſenſe, will offer to ſay.</p>
            <p>The laſt Objection of the Nonconformiſts, which under this head I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed in my <hi>Addreſs</hi> was, that <hi>Our Ceremonies are unneceſſary, and therefore ought not to be impoſed.</hi> To which I there returned a two fold Anſwer; Firſt, That <hi>what ſome may think unneceſſary, others may judge Expedient:</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>ſuppoſing,</hi> but not granting, <hi>that our Governours were faulty in impoſing ſome needleſs things upon us, Yet that our Compliance even with ſuch things for Peace and Unity's ſake, would rather be a Vertue than a Sin.</hi> In return to which he tells me firſt, that what I <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oiouſly ſuppoſe,</hi> is a plain Truth, and in effect con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt by us, <hi>viz.</hi> That our Ceremonies <hi>are unneceſſary, becauſe we declare them to be indiſſerent.</hi> But will this Man never leave Trifling with the Ambigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Words? If by <hi>unneceſſary,</hi> he m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ans <hi>not abſolutely and perpetually neceſſary to Salvation;</hi> I grant, that every indifferent thing is in this Senſe <hi>unneceſſary:</hi> But if by unneceſſary, he means <hi>altogether uſeleſs and inſignificant to any good purpoſe;</hi> I deny that what is in it's own nature indifferent, is always thus to be judged <hi>unneceſſary.</hi> For there may be ſuch Circumſtances of things and Perſons, wherein ſuch things may be Inſtruments and occaſions of much good: And accordingly, it is very evident, that the retaining of the uſe of ſome indifferent things in our Church, did not a little contribute to the advancing of the Reformation amongſt us, and bringing over many there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, who otherwiſe would not probably have to eaſily forſaken Popery: And I have already given my Reaſons why it is not ſit or proper, as matters ſtand, wholly now to lay all ſuch things aſide.</p>
            <p>In the next place he tells me, That <hi>he knows of no Command of Chriſt for comply<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng with Governours, in their unneceſſary impoſitions, for the ſake of Peace and Unity; and therefore he will not own it to be a Vertue rather than a Sin.</hi> I am ſorry that he is ſo ignorant of the Laws of the Goſpel: But, ſeriouſly, has he never heard of a Command of Chriſt, which the Apoſtle thus delivers to us, <hi>If it be poſſible as much as lyeth in you live Peaceably with all Men:</hi> Rom. 12. 18. If then a thing be otherwiſe never ſo unneceſſary, yet <hi>if it be poſſible;</hi> and if no Law of God has forbidden it, but that it <hi>lyeth in us,</hi> and we are at liberty to do it; we ought to comply with it, if it be neceſſary in order to Peace. Or has he never met with another Command, which S. <hi>Paul</hi> thus ſets down, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 1. <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t every Soul be ſubject to the higher Powers;</hi> And S. <hi>Peter</hi> thus, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. And to which there is no other exception made in the whole word of God, but only this, that <hi>we ought to obey God rather than Men? A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts</hi> 5. 29. If then a thing be commanded by the <hi>higher Powers,</hi> and <hi>Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> by the Authority of thoſe <hi>Men,</hi> in whom the Legiſlature reſides; How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever unneceſſary it may be thought to be; yet ſtill it is to be <hi>ſubmitted to,</hi> except it appears to be forbidden by ſome Law of Almighty God. But our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:37665:29"/> Author it ſeems would bring Government to a very Fine paſs, when he would make every private Man to be Judge, not only whether the thing Commanded be agree<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble to the Law of God; but alſo whether there were any n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceſſity for iſſuing ſuch a Command at all; before he ſhall lye under any Obligation to give Obedience to it.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Church-Governours,</hi> ſays he, <hi>are obliged to teach us, to obſerve no more than what Chriſt Commanded them, Mat. 28. 20. Acts</hi> 10. 33. I grant it. But what can be more plain than that the Apoſtles, who were the firſt Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors appointed by Chriſt to his Church, did teach all men to obſerve the Lawful Commands of Lawful Authority? And will our Author ſay that they had no Command from Chriſt for doing this? But ſays he again, <hi>they have no Power to impoſe things needleſs.</hi> I anſwer, that they who have the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of making Laws, ought not indeed to enact ſuch Laws, as impoſe things altogether uſeleſs to any good purpoſe: Nor are there any of our Church Conſtitutions, but what, if they were duly reſpected and obſerved, would tend very much to Order and Decency; and alſo <hi>to keep out unneceſſary Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatious;</hi> and therefore they cannot juſtly be termed <hi>needleſs things.</hi> But if I ſhould Judge them to be altogether <hi>needleſs;</hi> Yet, as long as they are <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent,</hi> this would be no good Reaſon, why I ſhould refuſe Obedience to them; as well becauſe I have no Warrant from Gods word for ſo doing; as that the Government in their Wiſdom, may have very good reaſon for Commanding ſuch things, altho', it may be, I am not able throughly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it. And that <hi>ſuch</hi> a modeſt <hi>compliance</hi> as this ſhould be judged no leſs than <hi>a Conſpiracy with Men uſurping Power,</hi> is ſuch an imagination as no Man of Reaſon or Charity could ever entertain.</p>
            <p>Well! But did not <hi>Paul withſtand</hi> Peter <hi>to the Face, in his impoſing unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary things on the Jews, Gal.</hi> 2. 11. But will this Man never make any Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of <hi>impoſing,</hi> not only impertinent but falſe Allegations of the Holy Scripture, upon his unwary Reader? S. <hi>Paul</hi> in the place mention'd, did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed withſtand S. <hi>Peter:</hi> But not on account of his <hi>Impoſing</hi> any thing <hi>on the Jews</hi> (of which there is not there the leaſt ſhadow of a ſuggeſtion) But purely for his <hi>Diſſimulation,</hi> in that by <hi>withdrawing</hi> and <hi>ſeparating himſelf</hi> from <hi>the Gentiles,</hi> for <hi>fear</hi> of <hi>them which were of the Circumciſion;</hi> he laid a ſtumbling Block before the Gentiles; And, tho' not by his Doctrine, yet by his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample ſeemed to put a ſort of <hi>Compulſion</hi> upon them, <hi>to live as did the Jews;</hi> to which no Law either of God or Man did oblige them. And, as to what he immediately Adds; I grant with him that the <hi>Authority which the Lord hath given</hi> unto the Church is <hi>for Edification,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 8. To which I muſt tell him, that a ſetled Decency and Order in the Circumſtances of Worſhip, does not a little conduce. I grant alſo, that where a Church ceaſes to <hi>fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt,</hi> we ought not therein to follow that Church, according to the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:37665:29"/> Apoſtles Doctrine, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1. But where the Church is careful to follow Chriſt in all manner of things that are n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ceſſary, and therein to the utmoſt to promote the Edification of all her Members, why it ſhould be a Sin to Comply with that Church, for Peace and Unity's ſake, in ſuch things as are indifferent, and therefore Lawful; or why a Man ſhould Renounce the Communion of ſuch a Church, on account of ſuch things, even in caſe they were needleſs; I cannot in the leaſt gather from either of thoſe places: And, whereas he tells us that <hi>the Synod of</hi> Jeruſilem, <hi>Acts</hi> 15, <hi>thought fit to impoſe nothing but neceſſary things,</hi> Verſe 28. I deſire to know in what Senſe was the <hi>abſtaining from Meats offered to Idols, and from blood, and from things ſtrangled,</hi> at that time <hi>neceſſary?</hi> If they were abſolutely neceſſary as eſſential parts of Gods Law, how comes S. <hi>Paul</hi> to teach the lawfulneſs of eating that which had been offered to an Idol, provided it were done without any Worſhip to the Idol, or Scandal given to weak Brethren? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> chap 8. and chap 10. And how came our Saviour ſo expreſsly to aſſure us, and in ſuch general Terms, that <hi>not that which goeth into the Mouth deſil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th a Man? Matt.</hi> 15. 11. But if they were in themſelves indifferent, and neceſſary only in order to reconcile the Jews, (who laid great Weight upon theſe things) and to bring them to a more favourable opinion of the Gentile Chriſtians, which I believe our Author will not deny; how can the Example of this Synod be alledged to Condemn, and not rather to juſtifie, the practiſe of the Eſtabliſhed Church; which has retained and kept up the uſe of ſome things, in themſelves likewiſe indifferent; becauſe they conceived them neceſſary and proper to reconcile thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (who by long cuſtom had entertained a great reſpect for them) and to beget in them a better opinion of the Reformation? And laſtly, as to what he quotes out of my Lord Primate <hi>Bramhall's Vindication;</hi> I freely grant, that no man ought to ſuffer an <hi>Erroneous Opinion</hi> to be <hi>impoſed</hi> upon him, becauſe as it is impoſſible for him to believe what he judges to be Erroneous; ſo to proſeſs what he does not believe, would be a lye and a ſin: But the conſequence which he would ſuggeſt from a ſuppoſed parity, between an <hi>Erroncous Opinion</hi> and an <hi>Indifferent</hi> (and therefore innocent) <hi>Ceremony</hi> or Circumſtance, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together weak and groundleſs.</p>
            <p>The fourth main Propoſition which I have inſiſted on in my Addreſs is, that <hi>ſince the Communion of our Church is lawful and innocent in it</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> (which, I hope, I have now abundantly proved againſt all that our Author <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s Objected to the contrary) <hi>there cannot be any juſt reaſon why the Nonc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſormiſts ſhould refuſe to join with us in it.</hi> And altho' our Author nibbles a little, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome of thoſe things which I have touched under this head of my Diſcourſe; yet ſince every thing, which he there ſays, is either not to the purpoſe, or elſe proceeds upon a ſuppoſition that our Communion is <hi>not lawful and innocent in it ſelf</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:37665:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:37665:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:37665:31"/> (which clearly alters the ſtate of the caſe, and the contrary whereto I have hitherto been aſſerting againſt all his weak and trifling Objections), I will not give either my ſelf or the Reader the trouble of making any Remarks upon the particulars of what he offers on this occaſion; only as to that paſſage of Dr. <hi>Holden</hi>'s, which he cites out of my Lord Primate <hi>Bramhall,</hi> p, 113. I think it enough to ſay, that altho' it may be <hi>leſs crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> for one National Church, <hi>upon account of ſome doubtful Opinions,</hi> or ſuch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> things, to refuſe the Communion of ſuch another Church (the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of whoſe particular Laws or Canons can only extend to its own mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers), than for ſubjects to diſobey thoſe Laws which are Enacted by their own lawful ſuperiors; and thereby to make a Schiſm in the very body of that National Church, of which they are or ought to be members: Yet ſince the obligation to Eccleſiaſtical Union and Communion is univerſal, and extends unto all Chriſtians and Churches whatſoever; wherever there is any ſeparation or breach of Communion, made between any Perſons, Churches, or Congregations, there muſt of neceſſity be a ſin on the one ſide or other; namely, on their part who give a juſt cauſe for breaking Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or on theirs who break it without any ſuch cauſe given: And this ſin is what I call by the name of a Schiſm.</p>
            <p>Having thus abundantly vindicated <hi>my Doctrine,</hi> I come now, in the laſt place of all, to that which our Author calls the <hi>uſe</hi> of it: In which my deſign was not (as he he ſuggeſts) <hi>to diſſwade the Non-Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>formiſts f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om the thoughts of a Legal Toleration;</hi> but only from the thoughts of ſuch a Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as might probably prove to be of dangerous conſequence to the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſht Church; if not to the Civil State alſo. And therefore, in Anſwer to all that our Author has offered upon this occaſion, I think it is enough for me to ſay, that I am not, nor ever was, againſt their having a full and free allowance to Worſhip God in their own way; or for cutting them ſhort in any advantages, which are conſiſtent with the publick peace and ſecurity of the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Eſtabliſhment; and if they deſire more than this, I appeal to all indifferent men whether it be reaſonable for the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to grant it to them.</p>
            <p>But before I make an end, I muſt take the pains to wipe off a little dirt, which our Author here alſo endeavours to caſt, as well upon me in particular, as upon the Eſtablibliſhed Church in general.</p>
            <p>Firſt then he tells me, p. 115. That I <hi>have low thoughts of Salvation;</hi> and <hi>rate it lower than employments of truſt and pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it upon Earth:</hi> For the former <hi>I ſeem to grant them liberty to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k;</hi> But the latter <hi>I would Monopoliz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to our own Party.</hi> But where I pray is the conſequence of this Argument? That I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend it as a thing of more dangerous conſequence to our ſafety and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, to admit the Nonconformiſts to a ſhare in the Government, than
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:37665:31"/> barely to permit them to ſeek for Eternal Salvation in their own way; is a truth that may well be gathered from what I have ſuggeſted in my Addreſs. But that therefore I ſet a greater value upon Temporal Employments, than upon everlaſting Salvation, is what no Man but one of our Authors Logick and Charity, would pretend to infer from any thing that I have ſaid. But that I <hi>would deprive them of the Ordinary means of ſubſiſting and ſerving God and their Countrey;</hi> which he there alſo lays to my Charge, but does not pretend to prove; is ſuch a bare-fac'd calumny, as no one but a Man that wanted Conſcience or Conſideration, would ever offer to load me with: For he who has but half an Eye, may very plainly ſee that it is very poſſible, and very <hi>ordinary</hi> too, for Men to ſubſiſt comfortably and grow Rich, and <hi>ſerve God and their Countrey</hi> faithfully in a private Station, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ever being put into any place of Power and Authority.</p>
            <p>He tells me, preſently after, That <hi>the Church may ſtand, tho' ſhe don't in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hance all Offices of Power, Truſt and Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. Theſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> are not the Rock, on which Chirſt built his Church.</hi> But whoever ſaid they were; Or to what purpoſe is this uncharitable inſinuation? I do not doubt or diſtruſt the good Providence and protection of Almighty God: But I cannot think it Reaſonable willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to put a Power into any Mans hands, which I have reaſon to fear that he will employ to my hurt, whenever he has a fair opportunity for it. Well! but <hi>that their deſign is not to overthrow our Church, is evident; becauſe they have not moved for the withdrawing either Power or Profit from us.</hi> But how ſhall we be ſecure, that they or their ſucceſſors never will make ſuch a motion, or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſuch a deſign? If they judge our legal Eſtabliſhment to be lawful, why do they not con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orm to it? But if unlawful, are they not then in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bound to uſe their beſt endeavours to get it altered.</p>
            <p>But whereas I had objected that the Presbyterian Party had formerly in all the three Kingdoms; and again lately in one of them, actually over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown the Eſtabliſh't Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopal Church; And that therefore there is much reaſon to fear that, if not at preſent, yet in ſucceeding times they may, if not carefully prevented, do the ſame thing again in this Kingdom; our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, inſtead of offering us any manner of ſecurity againſt ſuch an impen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent evil; freely ſuppoſes the truth of what I have ſaid, and tells me, p. 117. That <hi>tho' all this ſhould come to paſs, yet it is ſevere juſtice to puniſh the Predeceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs, for the probable faults o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Succeſſors, not as yet comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tted: In <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ell there is more juſtice, where Men are only puniſht for real and paſt Crimes.</hi> Which is plainly in other words to ſay, that tho' we clearly foreſee the ruine of our ſelves, or our Poſterity, by granting all that the Nonconformiſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; yet we muſt not take any care to prevent it. Here is a ſample of thoſe <hi>modeſt Petitions</hi> of which our Author ſpeaks in his Preface. But the Objection it ſelf is moſt weak and fooliſh. For altho' it is not juſt to <hi>pun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſh</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:37665:32"/> any Man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r a Crime not as yet committed; yet to prevent Men from committing a crime in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is likely that they may run; and by ſuch prudent caution, to ſave the Church and State fro a confu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion or ruine; was never, I believe, accounted as a piece of Injuſtice: And more than this I never thought of, or pleaded for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But,</hi> ſays our Author, <hi>the Conſequences of denying this Toleration deſired, will be burtful,</hi> viz. 1. <hi>The diſcouraging of many induſtrious and proſitable Subjects.</hi> 2. <hi>The alienating the affections of all ſober men from Church-men, who are the ſole oppoſers of this deſire.</hi> 3. <hi>An impoſſibility ever hereafter to induce the Non-Conformiſts to join with us, if there ſhould be occaſion for their ſervice.</hi> All which I grant might have a fair appearance of truth, if ſo be that a Toleration were really denyed to the Non-Conformiſts. But ſince the caſe is quite otherwiſe, and that a free and legal Tol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ration is offered them, upon the very ſame terms with which thoſe of their perſwaſion in <hi>England</hi> are well ſatisfied; which is as great an encouragement as can be to every thing, except the ambition of a few Leading-men among them: If this Toleration be refuſed by themſelves; and if the Penal Laws, which are ſtill in force in this Kingdom, ſhould ever liereafter come to be put in Execution againſt them; I deſire to know who but their own Leading-men will be to be blamed for it? Who it ſeems are not contented to have their <hi>indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Labourers, ingenious Artiſts, and honeſt Traders</hi> (as our Author ſpeaks of them in his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, ſecured from trouble, and encouraged in their honeſt employments; if they at the ſame time muſt be excluded from offices of power and truſt in the Civil State. So that the true and only reaſon why an Act of Toleration is not here paſſed as well as in <hi>England,</hi> is becauſe a few men among the Non-Conformiſts do obſtinately refuſe to ſacrifice their ambition to the peace and ſafety of their Brethren.</p>
            <p>But our Author taxes us with <hi>ungrateful breaking the promiſes which we made to the</hi> Non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts, <hi>and diſcovering heart-enmity againſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m.</hi> But when he thus draws up his Indictments, he ought to produce his proofs; for he has hitherto given us no great reaſon to believe him upon his bare word. It was, and I think i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtill, the opinion of all ſober men among us, that the Non-Conformiſts ought to have a free Tol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ration upon ſuch terms as may be conſiſtent with the ſafety of the Eſtabliſhed Church and Civil State; (which ſhews that we bear no <hi>heart-enmity</hi> againſt them) and 'tis, I think, their own fault if they refuſe it. But if more than this was ever; promiſed them by us; I deſire our Author to let us know when, and by whom, and what Authority they had to make ſuch promiſes to them.</p>
            <p>As for the buffoon ſtory of <hi>a ſool, a quart of ale, and a gallows at the Bridge of Stirling,</hi> with which our Author concludes his Book: All that I can gather from it is, that, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all his pretences to Sanctity and tenderneſs of Conſcience, he is not a man of that ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which becomes a Miniſter of the Goſpel: Otherwiſe he would never have ſo imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently pulled in ſuch a nonſenſical piece in a matter of ſuch weighty concern as the Peace and Unity of the Church. And <hi>thus I</hi> likewiſe <hi>conclude that there can be no harm done by his Anſwer to my Addreſs;</hi> except men will be ſo fooliſh as to be impoſed on by a bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dle of Sophiſtry and Calumny, without any manner of ſound or ſolid Proof.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37665:32"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
